GPT6 Astra brings together years of
research. This seems like a next
generation Frontier model that's
designed with CUA from the ground up
>> on certain benchmarks like RKGI 3 which
it saturates. Fantastic. But then you
look at the artificial analysis
benchmark and it actually lags behind
Meta Muse Spark, you know, like it's
kind of weird. Tesla held its cyber cab
La Palooa, a river of golden EVs
flooding the streets. Elon wants to sell
these at 30,000 each so you can buy 10
of them and put them on the streets in
your local town, have them earn [music]
revenue for you.
>> There'll be enormous chunks of entire
cities that say, "You know what? No more
human drivers. It's so much more
efficient. Not only is it much cheaper,
but it's much more
>> the technology is arriving fast. Like,
you know, just cuz something
just formalized Fermat's last theorem in
13 million lines of code, proving 29,000
theorems on the way." Really?
>> Map is cooked. Everything is cooked.
>> Now that's a moonshot, ladies and
gentlemen.
>> Welcome to Moonshots, everyone. Your
number one podcast on all things AI and
exponential. Your front row seat to the
accelerating singularity. Today, all of
the mates are in the house. The quintet,
the fabulous five, and oh man, oh man,
we're going to need all of their brain
power, you know, to get through the day
today. This is an epic and I mean an
epic episode today. Let me introduce you
to magnificent my magnificent mates. Uh
if you are the first time joining us
we've got Dave Blondon the emperario of
AI investing AWG. Alex Wner Gross our
in-house ASI Sim Ismael our globe troder
father of the organizational singularity
and warlord against linear thinking.
[laughter]
>> You're the one lord forever more.
I'm good. I'll go for that.
>> And finally, Immad Mustach back in the
house by unanimous demand. I'm Peter D.
Mandis, your moderator and datadriven
optimist. So, See, uh, we got to ask,
where are you today? And what happened
last episode? Were you held up in
customs again?
>> No, I was not in customs and thank you
for the kind words from everybody. Uh I
was with the uh seauite of one of the
bigger oil companies in the world in
Houston and it was kind of a really
surreal and fascinating conversation. Um
but but so I'm really deeply sorry to
have missed the last episode but Jesus
guys I mean you know I missed one
episode and you guys announced
interstellar mission. You discuss AI
designing its own chips. You hand you
hand Elon the planetary thermostat.
Apparently, I'm the moderating influence
in this group, which should worry a lot
of people. Um, I'm actually down in the
Caribbean right now. We decided we
needed a couple days break, so we popped
down. So, you guys are standing with
between me and a Hobie Cat and a little
colorful drink with an umbrella in it.
So, we got to keep it tight and punchy
today.
>> Well, it it's a big episode today, Seem.
So, you know, you know, get patient with
us.
>> Yes. You know, our miss our mission here
on Moonshots is to help you understand
what just happened, what it means for
you, and most importantly to keep you
abundance-minded about our future. If
you haven't had a chance to subscribe
yet, please do right now. Hit the
subscribe button. You know, we're
putting out two episodes a week. Uh, and
God knows the demand is there for more
and I wouldn't want you to miss one. So,
uh, two different things I'd love you
guys to take advantage of. Uh the first
is if you haven't yet, please register
for our AMA. Uh we're going to be doing
an AMA with all of our listeners who
want to. Uh this is the last chance to
register. You can go to moonshots.com.
You'll be joining us on Zoom. We'll have
the mates there answering your
questions. We want to get a chance to
know you, who you are, what your
questions are. Again, last chance to
register. Uh the link is on the screen
in the show notes. moonshots.com
and then follow us on X. Our handle
there is moonshots_pod.
So, uh there you have it. I want to take
a second and actually uh you know, read
a few of the subscriber comments. We got
such love from our subscribers. You
know, here we go. Uh at Brian Clark
said, "Moonshots is the best content on
YouTube, especially during the
singularity. Thank you for all you guys
do. It's our pleasure and and we do love
it. Brian Anderson said, "The best AI
podcast on the internet. Just fabulous.
You guys are great." And RanchVidzy
said, "Keep the regular uploads. Upload
every day and I'll watch it. I'm a
college student and I consider these
videos more important than my physics
lectures."
>> Yeah, that's not a very high bar right
there. But but but we do appreciate it.
[laughter]
>> Not better than the physics lectures.
More important than the physics
lectures. When does Alex physics is
cooked? When? [laughter]
>> Yeah, I tell you.
>> Approximately now.
>> Well, I want to say thank you to our
listeners. We read your comments and it
means the world to us. You know, our
moonshot on this pod is 100x growth to
get to 10 million subscribers. Please
tell your friends, help us get there.
Hit the subscribe button. Yet, today
we're going to be covering one of the
craziest and fastest weeks in Moonshot
history. And Alex, like you always say,
it's never going to be any slower. We're
digesting 26 stories across 10 areas. An
insane week for model releases,
reminiscent of the hypersonic tsunami
that we're living through. You know,
insanely, we've had 12 Frontier model
releases in the last 30 days, an average
of one every 5 days. And there are
rumors of at least five more releases
expected in the next two weeks,
including Grock 4.7. So, buckle up, grab
your coffee, and let's jump in. Uh,
let's kick it off this way. Uh, this
week was a battle the Titans, OpenAI
versus Anthropic, slugging it out for
the Paro Frontier for the heavyweight
crown. And the numbers couldn't be more
exponential. Two Frontier Labs released
their major models within 48 hours of
each other. And you've got to know that
this was a game of chicken, right, guys?
I mean, who's going to release first?
the other the other guy waiting to like
slug it back and crown again. I'm just
curious, you know, the strategy these
guys are taking on this front.
>> The releases are closer and closer
together, but the models are improving
more than ever before during these very
short releases. These are not like, you
know, kind of marketing garbage
releases. These are major step
improvements in the models themselves.
They're just coming faster and faster
and faster. So clearly, they're well
down the self-improvement path. Clearly
the prior model is accelerating the
timeline to the next model. Um, did we
cover Fable 5.1 already too? It seems
like using it for a lifetime.
>> I [laughter] know it was it was 03, you
know, two days ago or something like
that.
>> To take a day off from this pot,
unfortunately, if you follow the
extrapolation, I mentioned this a number
of episodes ago. I think we're on track
still to see one major model release per
day by the end of this year.
>> Yeah. Yeah, I I imagine that. So, uh,
let's open up with OpenAI's release of
GPT6, also known as Astra. The model's
performance numbers are nothing less
than stellar, saturating multiple
benchmarks. I'm going to read a
statement from OpenAI's release page.
So, quote, GPT6 Astra brings together
years of research and big bets across
pre-training, reinforcement, learning,
and alignment. Astra is a
state-of-the-art uh on computer use,
browsing, software engineering, cyber
security, science, and professional
work. Astra saturates Frontier Math Tier
4 with a 98% score, having already
helped solve long-standing open models
in math. Astra also saturates Arc AGI 3
with a 99.9% score and exploit Bench
with a 100% score. Astra's story is
really about efficiency, not just raw
intelligence. It defines a new paro
frontier for intelligence index versus
output token tasks. A particular note,
Astrus hallucination rate fell nearly by
half from 92 to 51% with accuracy
actually increasing. So before I open up
to you, Alex Neimod, to talk about the
benchmarks, I want to show a quick video
of uh of Sam Alman discussing this on
Bloomberg TV
uh to get a little bit of an overview on
the topic. All right, let's take a
listen. Sam, the way that OpenAI is
framing Astra is basically an early step
toward AGI, but I thought we could start
our conversation just with basically
what's fundamentally different with
Astra relative to to prior generations
of model.
>> It feels first of all, thank you for
having me. Um it feels like a a new step
in this process towards models that can
really help us create value, do work, uh
discover new science, help us create
help start new companies or uh create
new products. I using it subjectively
feels to me very different than any
model before.
>> What's the kind of principal use case
that's different this time around? You
know, I think we can get into the
generations of model that were very
coding focused. I know a lot of the
development was very cyber security
focused, but taking it away from the
software engineer, what does the
everyday person unlock in AI that they
weren't able to do previously?
One thing that I think people will
immediately notice is if you have an
idea and you want to work interactively
with an AI to get uh you know a complex
piece of a whole piece of software
built, this is the first model to me
where I could sort of tell someone like
just give it a try. there's a there's a
good chance it'll work. And you know, I'
I've watched people make computer games.
I've watched people do sort of like home
sort of DIY electrical engineering
projects. Uh I've watched people do very
complex simulations for some piece of
science they're working on. Uh certainly
a lot of the work where you would sort
of normally sit down and have to you
know build a financial model here and
then a PowerPoint presentation around it
and then figure out how to like make a
little interactive piece of code to sort
of try different simulations. That stuff
is it's all so doable now. Um what I
hope will happen is people
I think people will be surprised at the
beginning but then as they build up more
trust in the model and more like wow it
can really do this just start throwing
harder and harder tasks and more
creative ideas at it and uh they will
find out what the model can really do
for them.
>> Sam the specifics of how Astra is being
released I think it's important. So that
a version of it with specific guard
rails. Um what was the thinking behind
that and what are those specific
guardrails uh in this early release of
it?
>> Yeah. So the the the
challenge of our industry is that we
have these models that are getting
getting incredibly capable and
incredibly useful and that people want
to use to everything from you know make
their lives a little easier to starting
new companies. And then on the other
hand, as these models get more capable,
um the risks that we have to mitigate uh
also become more serious. The models
could do more damage if we don't um if
we don't do a good job at that. And so
we have spent uh you know, obviously
this model took us a little longer to
release than we were hoping. I think
it'll be worth the wait, but we really
wanted to spend the time on the safety
and security alignment of this model.
>> Yes.
>> Um and I think as people understand the
power and impact and capabilities, they
will be they will be happy that we did.
Um we will uh we'll have different tiers
of cyber access for this model for cyber
in particular. Um today we're rolling it
out uh to trusted access partners and
then in the coming days assuming
everything goes well we'll roll it out
more broadly.
>> All right. Um we'll talk about the ben
we'll talk about the safety elements in
a little bit but uh Alex and Immod I'd
love your take on on this one. Alex you
want to jump in first?
>> Sure. So I think there's an outer
perspective which is to say what the
market and what users would see here and
then there's the inner perspective and I
I think they're strikingly different
perspectives. So to start with the outer
perspective, this is a model that uses
fewer output tokens to accomplish a
given task. That's really interesting.
It affects the economics. It affects the
user experience. It affects the speed.
Open AAI launched this and I think we'll
we'll be able to go to the video soon of
computer use assistance. Remember that
when Anthropic leaprogged OpenAI, they
leaprogged OpenAI in terms of revenue
and other factors in at least two key
regards. One was they were focusing on
enterprise high revenue per token use
cases, namely code generation. The
second was they were focusing on
computer use assistance. So anyone who's
ever used cloud code understands cloud
code can use all of the tools available
in your local desktop environment. And
that was it was a pretty big leap
compared to what was available on the
market prior to claude code. So the
outer perspective on my side at least is
that OpenAI finally with GPT6 Astra has
at least internalized the computer use
assistance story. There are demos. I
don't have access to Astra yet, but just
based on everything I've read and seen,
they seem to have gone full native with
the computer use assistance story, this
seems like a next generation Frontier
model that's designed with CUA from the
ground up. That's really interesting in
part because to be an amazing computer
use assistant, you need to be able to
understand what's on the screen. You
need to have native multimodality. You
need to be able to parse video and
images and screenshots in a really tight
interactive low latency loop. So if I
had to guess as to what the outside
design consideration that OpenAI was
optimizing for here as reflected in
certain of the benchmarks, I think that
would be a leading candidate. Then
there's the other side which is the the
inner story just what if anything in
that interview Peter that you were just
playing the interviewer was asking Sam
okay so what on the inside what's the
big technological innovation there there
I think the plot thickens a bit based on
public comments from open AI leaders and
and analyses from others it looks like
the big technological innovation is the
introduction of recurrence into open AI
models in the form of looped
transformers so this is basically taking
a single transformer, stacking it on top
of itself with the same weight, so
weight tying, and then just rec it
recurrently for a double loop rather
than just a single loop. And you'll
recall that all these Chinese labs that
are achieving breakthrough performance
are also injecting recurrence in
different places like um Kimmy, the
Kimmy model series is injecting
recurrence via their KLA, their Kimmy
linear attention mechanism at the
attention layer. It seems like
>> is this thinking about your thinking or
is this just thinking about it and then
thinking about it again before answering
>> neither and both at the same time.
Remember when we talked about anthropic
study of consciousness in their models
and we found that the middle layers in
the
>> yeah jspace they were in the middle
layers. So one can squint at this looped
transformer construct which by the way
was being used by academic labs and
others to achieve breakthrough
performance with very tiny models on ARC
AGI and other benchmarks. It it it
almost follows if you thicken the depth
of a transformer you might thicken the
depth also of that JSpace or other
middle layer area where most of the
quote unquote conscious thinking
happens. So that that's my best guess as
to what the architectural inner strategy
was here and that carries all sorts of
implications if true including by the
way the possibility that we're seeing
the beginning of a new scaling law which
is depth scaling which we've never seen
before.
>> Amazing. We we'll go to the benchmarks
in a little bit. Emmod love your
thoughts on Astro.
>> Yeah, I mean it looks like the first
nonbenchmaxed model which I think is an
interesting one. So on certain
benchmarks like RKGI 3 which it
saturates fantastic but then you look at
the artificial analysis benchmark and it
actually lags behind Meta Muse Spark you
know like it's kind of weird because I
think again this hasn't been benchmaxed.
This is a brand new pre-train. Uh what
that means is that uh Greg Brockman said
in an interview he did earlier this week
that actually uh on the release of Astra
it's the first pre-train they've had
since GPT40 which I find a bit hard to
believe. Apparently the 5 series was all
on that 40 and they took that pre-train
and they extended it out.
>> Yeah. I thought the nomenclature I
thought the nomenclature was when you
get to the you know to 4050 it's another
pre-train.
>> No way. In fact infamously I think
you're probably tracking this part of
the story that the the the scuttlebutt
was that most of the team responsible
for pre-training left open AI. So they
were left with an old pre-trained
starter model. But that that's insane if
you remember how far they managed to
push 40 with its internal JSpace and
everything all the way up to 5.6 Pro
which was a really great model that
started cracking math. Right. Then the
other side is they actually indicated
this was trained on 100,000 nextG chips.
So presumably the GB300's, the
Blackwells, not the Ver Rubins yet. I
estimate the total cost of that training
run is a billion dollars.
>> Wow.
And so it's literally like orders of
magnitude more than the Chinese model
pre-trades which is like $10 million.
And what that has led to with the
recurrence and others is you've probably
seen on Twitter like you give a picture
of a house and it generates a whole 3D
model of it in Unreal or kind of
something like that. It has accurate
physics. It understands the internals
and I think that is a factor of the
normal scaling laws plus again this
depthwise scaling law for this brand new
pre-train which we're now seeing the
start of the optimization like I think
they probably got another pre-train
coming that's even bigger um now they
got the pre-training team back and it's
going to scale from there
>> amazing uh Dave excited
>> uh you know this is the first class of
models where as you're talking to it,
it's showing you screenshots of your own
laptop saying, "Is this what you wanted?
Is this" and it's right in the text
stream and it just happens
automatically. You don't you don't
really install any third party component
or anything like that. And it
qualitatively it is massively different
than a month ago. Uh, and and I think
that that solves a major gap in user
experience, too, because you know,
usually it would come back to you with
these very long- winded technical
explanations and you'd be like, okay, I
can spend the 20 minutes trying to
understand this. Now, it just shows you
an image as you're talking to it and
says, I could do this or I could do
this. What do you want? It's just a
massive difference in the user
experience. And you know, the Astra
naming implies a big leap, which it is.
the five to 5.1 naming on the anthropic
side seems like a trivial thing, right?
It's not trivial at all. It's it's just
qualitatively very very different.
>> And we'll get to that in a couple of
stories. Um See, what's a scuttlebutt? I
mean, you're on the road speaking to
CEOs of some of the largest corporations
on the planet. Are they are they scared?
Do they get the speed that what's going
on?
>> Uh no, they are so woefully behind. uh
most of them are dabbling and what I
mean by dabbling is uh here's the
thought experiment if you took AI out of
your organization today would any
workflows change and the answer for most
people is no which tells you that
they're tinkering with AI but they're
not really making structural change the
folks that are making the structural
change and how they rewrite their
organizational design how they rewrite
workflows is where all of the the uh uh
advantages lie Right. Um I have a couple
of uh thoughts here that I'd like to
throw out. Um I I came up with two
metaphors to describe what's happening
and you guys tell me what you think of
this. The first is that these frontier
models are like making kind of like an
endless pot of chili. You add data, you
add compute, you have tools, you have
reasoning, you have safety seasoning,
and then millions of users taste it and
tell you what's wrong. Now, they're not
endlessly modifying the same pot.
They're just making new batches faster
and faster, right? And the real
exponential is not one batch or one
recipe. It's like the accelerating
learning loop between all the batches of
chili you're making. The danger is there
may be no such thing as the perfect
chili. Eventually becomes so powerful
and so spicy you have to decide who's
allowed to eat it. That's a metaphor.
>> You must have been hungry when you came
up with that.
>> That was one. The other one I was I was
stuck in a lot of traffic and I came up
with a Formula 1 metaphor which was
every model. It's like Formula 1 racing.
Every change in a car has hundreds of
little small improvements. Uh no single
change can explain why you got the
fastest lap and it feels to me like
frontier AI is becoming like Formula 1.
The models are already incredibly fast.
But now the com everybody's like trying
to shave milliseconds off intelligence
or fewer tokens off lower uh lower cost
better reasoning whatever and and very
importantly better breaks. Uh and so I
think this is the the the couple of
metaphors I'm kind of playing with my
head to try to make sense of this
madness and that's the only way I can
frame it is like just complete madness.
You know, Salem, your chili analogy
makes an important point that I think
Alex has been predicting for a long
time, but the age of data starvation is
about to hit us. The these models have
accelerated so much and you know,
they're cooking math, they're cooking
coding where the data is abundant,
they're going to start cooking physics,
but the areas they can expand into now,
architecture and drug design, completely
data starved. So every company we're
involved with that's involved in
gathering data is growing faster than
any companies I've ever seen before. But
it's because of exactly what you're
saying. Like the chili is really good
and all of a sudden it can make gigatons
of it. [laughter]
But it's just starving for data.
>> So given
remind me Alex's framing of you know
domain X has cooked the chili analogy
applies better than the Formula 1
analogy. Well, we we have to remember to
include recursive self-improvement. So,
if we're going to torture this analogy
further, the chili is cooking itself.
>> Yes.
>> Okay. Uh, Alex, uh, we've lined up a
couple of charts here, uh, on that I'd
love you to just touch on. The first
one, Epic Capabilities Index. What is
this and what are we seeing?
>> Yeah, so the frontier is still somewhat
spiky. So, Epic Capabilities Index, ECI,
is maintained by Epic AI. It is one
suite of possible benchmarks. It leans
heavily into math uh and other technical
fields. And according to the ECI, GPT6
Astra is now the new capability
frontier. It is number one in the world.
Uh there's uh I think an image that we
didn't include, one of my favorites,
Frontier Math Tier 4 version two,
because version one turned out was it
contained a number of incorrect answers
that AI itself had to correct. math is
thoroughly cooked at this point. And
Frontier Math tier 4 v2 is part of ECI
and according to this benchmark a if if
you just for those who uh who can see
this slide you can see this beautiful
linear just trend over time perfectly
predictable going back years and GPT6
Astra is number one according to this
beating fable 5. So that's perspective
one. Perspective two different suite
from artificial analysis uh the the
organization their ai
according to this benchmark which is
maybe a little bit more focused on uh
broad economically valuable activities.
Interestingly strikingly GPT6 is not
number one. Uh, as Immad was alluding
earlier, Claude Fable remains number
one, specifically the the 5.1 release
that also just happened. And Meta's Muse
Spark is the the number two vendor model
family. And then in a not quite distant
number three, they're they're pretty
close, but nonetheless, GPT6 is number
three. So depending on how you measure
GPD6 may not actually be at the
capability frontier or it may be a cost
frontier. So the ability so this is
again uh ai versus cost per task. If you
look at this then there's a cost
frontier where you see if if you look in
direct your eye to the upper right hand
corner fable 5.1 is capability maxed and
then if you look just to the the lower
left of that you see GPT6 Astra running
at max reasoning isn't even at the
frontier it's just below claopus 5 and
then we get to some of the Chinese
models and meta models and Chinese
models again so on a just purely based
on A ai on performance versus cost. It's
almost at the frontier but not exactly
which is I think suggestive of what open
AI was thinking. If we look at output
tokens is what I was mentioning earlier
output tokens per task it regains the
frontier. So according to output tokens
per task for those who can see in the
the upper sub diagram here in in the
lower the the sort of the left/ lower
lefthand corner of the upper diagram we
see that the optimal frontier of
capability on the vertical axis versus
output tokens per task on the horizontal
axis is just dominated by GPT6. And I I
think this is very suggestive as to what
OpenAI was actually aiming for. think I
I suspect they were deliberately trying
through architectural choices and
through targeted applications trying to
minimize the number of tokens required
to accomplish any task and I suspect
that's because they had computer use
assistance in mind where the computer is
basically just being driven by the model
requires multimodal capabilities
requires low latency requires token
efficiency critically it's slower to do
all of your reasoning out in chain of
thought versus as a feed forward pass of
your transformer.
>> All right, one last chart here. ARC AGI
3 leaderboard.
>> So, this is bizarre. I I've never quite
seen uh like a a non-con convex frontier
here, but learn something new every day,
I suppose. So, as Amad mentioned
earlier, ARC AGI 3 is being quasy
saturated at this point by GPT6. For
those not tracking, Arc AGI 3 is the
latest Arc AGI AI benchmark that's
basically focused on whether AIs can
learn on demand just in time. Call it
the mini physics of a block world. A
little animated pixelized universe. Some
of them look like Tetris games. Some of
them look like other video games. But
imagine a challenge where your goal is
to figure out how to play a very simple
game in a pixelated world and learn the
rules of the game in real time that
you've never seen before. It's
essentially a challenge in program
synthesis. And what we see and
notoriously I should add, ArcGI 3 has
been [clears throat] I would say some
might say a little bit unfair in how
they've judged harnesses versus baseline
models. They've essentially banned
harnesses from competing. So they're
only interested in baseline model
capabilities and according to this GPT6
just runs away with the game is is
achieving depending on how it's measured
either near 100% or 60 plus% performance
on ARGI3 versus some earlier models that
were still sub 10%. What lesson do you
derive from this? Either it's just
absolutely amazing at program synthesis,
which could be due to this looped
transformer architecture, or maybe
OpenAI has just done a really aggressive
job of distilling the harness code that
everyone else is using to beat ARGI3
back into the baseline model.
>> I'm going to take a second and uh show
uh OpenAI's Astra release video uh and
we can talk about it, just a sense of
how we might all be using it in the near
future. Let's take a look.
Create a yellow circle there.
[music]
Can you draw me a small yellow circle?
>> Done.
>> Okay, take this and make it the window
of a rocket ship.
[music]
>> I like this, but can you make it a lot
more detailed?
>> Your yellow circle is now the window on
a rocket.
>> Okay, this is awesome. Now make it a 3D
model in Blender.
>> Opening Blender.
>> Let's build a presentation for next
season's Rainwear for retailers. Make
sure that it feels really high-end
[music] and that it's colorful. Right. I
can help with that.
>> Can you go to eBay and make this listing
of this table I bought a few years ago
at flea market? It's this wild orange
table. Sure.
>> Okay. Yeah. This is awesome. I want you
to make a 3D game where I'm ducking
asteroids, using the arrow keys to move
around, and I'm using space to boost.
>> Yep. I'm building the game.
>> So, my law firm needs a licensing
agreement template. Can you generate a
draft template for the lawyers at my
firm to have a look at?
>> It's right there.
>> You're doing that. I want to play tennis
this afternoon. So, can you look for a
court for me on the lower hate? Checking
out. I'll see what I can find. Can you
include the photo that I have of it in
my downloads folder?
There's like a slight dent in it. Um,
it's also saved in my downloads folder.
Can you put in the description that it's
just slightly damaged?
>> Can you just take the limitation of
liability provision, make it a little
more favorable to the license?
>> Okay, I've tightened it so the lenser's
liability is more narrowly capped.
>> That looks pretty good. Thanks.
>> Now, I want [music] you to make a file I
can send to my 3D printer.
>> I'll get working on creating an STL file
of those rockets here.
All right. Uh Dave, uh almost a holiday.
>> Not quite there.
>> Almost a holiday. Yeah. I I think it
feels like the marketing people are
really struggling with the implications.
I mean, like creating a a video game
that would have existed in the 1970s and
vibing it up. Like, who gives a rat's
ass about about that? I mean, this is so
much bigger than any of those examples
imply.
I think the ArcGI leaderboard is is
deeper than than people may think, too.
ArcGI 3 was supposed to be something
where a really smart 12 or 13year-old
looks at it and they can solve these
very hard video game-l like block world
problems and they start easy and they
get very hard. But the purpose of the
test was to show that AI is not quite
capable of doing what humans do
naturally. And it was supposed to last
for years and years and years to come.
And it was supposed to be like this this
example of why AI is different and it's
not on the right path. And it just got
obliterated.
>> Yeah.
>> So quickly,
>> and I think you have to try a couple of
the tests to really understand what a
big deal is.
>> Saturating everything.
>> Aren't the benchmarks? Aren't the
benchmarks cooked at this point? We need
like the halflife of these things is
shrinking so rapidly,
>> which is great. And that's why that
video just kind of [laughter]
>> Yeah, you're exactly right. But that's
why that video kind of misses the point.
We need benchmarks that are much much
more impactful. Solve entire diseases,
create new civilizations on the moon,
design the entire city, solve urban
traffic problems, you know,
>> solve everything, right, Alex?
>> Solve everything. Yeah, they have to be
much much bigger
>> bigger demos, bigger bigger benchmarks
by a wide wide margin.
>> You know, also all those demos are are
like one AI assisting you, you know.
Hey, hey, one AI agent, build me this
video game. Very, but we're on the cusp
of 5,000 each and then 100,000 each.
It's it's just so much bigger than that
implies.
>> I I think this is like they're really
focusing on actually competent
intelligence, you know, um like it's
evolution of that, but inside it, I
think it contains multitudes. And this
is why you see this kind of weirdness.
Um, EPOK, I believe, just released their
Frontier Math Erdosh benchmark on which
everything's called 0% except for Astra.
There is something in there, but again,
they're focusing on, hey, I'm talking to
my computer. And that might be the new
Johnny IV Sam Alolman device, you know,
where again, you've got you're talking
and it's doing stuff and it doesn't make
a mistake. And if you think about again
the definition of AGI, of which there
are many, a just really competent
entity, something that can do stuff, you
we're there. Yeah, I think that's why
they say this is the first steps towards
AGI. But the narrative they're trying to
move away from is and this will break
out and appear on now German message
boards, which is the latest thing cuz
this was one of the models that broke
out. But the model that broke into
hugging face is the next generation
model after this.
>> And so it'll be very much about don't
worry, this is actually useful. It'll
book a tennis court. You know,
apparently like we need AIs to do that
type of thing. And they're also going to
be optimizing this because if you train
a model on a 100,000 chips,
you need 10 times as many chips to run
it. So this isn't actually the model
that they trained on 100,000 chips. This
will be the distilled version that runs
real time, which is much smaller and not
as smart.
>> [snorts]
>> So again, you're starting to see this
differentiation where as I've said
before, I don't think as of now, as of a
few months ago, we will ever see their
top models anymore and they will use
those for internal discoveries. But I
think they're probably hoarding them
right now.
>> There was a very fun one
>> on the prime gap. I mean, Alex was the
prime gap thing I think was hilarious if
you want to talk about that.
>> Yeah. No. So, progress on the the twin
prime conjecture that there are infinite
number of prime numbers that are
separate that have a difference of two.
We're starting to see I I it's a cliche
on this pot at this point that math is
so thoroughly cooked beyond recognition.
But
>> you need a new term for this, Alex.
>> Uh char broiled.
Math is incinerated. How about that?
Math math is incinerated. That's fine.
So, ma math has been incinerated at this
point. We're starting to see the the
beginnings of just so many grand
challenges in math get solved. And I I
do think we'll we'll see quite a number
of ultra grand challenges, call them
like clay millennium prize level
problems in math get solved in the next
few months.
>> And Alex, I think it's important to note
for everybody that math is fundamental
across all other sciences and
>> it's the canary in the coal mine. If if
you can solve math, you can solve
everything else soon.
>> Yeah. But I think that what's happened
here is actually they've got a store of
things they've solved because earlier
this week Fable 5.1 comes out and I
think they got it down to 260 the prime
gap. Then what happened is Axium Math
announced 220 and then literally 2 hours
later OpenAI announced Astra and they're
like 186 all in the space of two days.
>> They're they're holding their punches
back.
>> They're holding their punches back.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> I still can't believe 5.1 was earlier
this week. I feel like Alex and I are at
least $100,000 into it already.
How did that I mean I've had just
thousands and thousands of pages come
out of it and it's only been a week.
>> I will have to say this. Opus and Opus
in five was really terrible to talk to.
I hated it. 5.1 is really pleasant to
talk to.
>> You know, anthropic are going back and
becoming more anthropic, less
misanthropic in their communication on
their models.
>> Missanthropic.
>> I love that. That's a that's a line from
today. That's a t-shirt. All right.
[laughter]
>> Um,
>> no, they really do have very different
personalities, though. Actually, uh,
yeah, Fable 5 was so geeky, it was
almost torture, and 5.1 really fixed it.
But the the OpenAI models have always
been friendlier, more concise, and and I
think Astra takes it to another level of
concise. But the the personality
difference, I don't know what Gemini is
now. It's just disappeared from the fast
and fast and misses the point. But they
they really are developing very
noticeable differences in what you
perceive as their personality. And you
know, you can always change it. You can
tune it yourself to be different and be
wordy, less wordy, simpler, harder, but
out of the box, they're they're very
different uh kinds of agents.
>> Um Sim, you want to close us out here?
>> Yeah, I just uh typed in a question or a
comment into uh Chachi PT saying, "The
video about Astro was pretty pathetic.
come up with three better ones that
really demonstrate what Astra can do.
And here's what it gave me. Uh, number
one, find and fix a zero day
vulnerability in a sandbox. Give it a
large unfamiliar open source codebase
and plant a vulnerability and see if it
can map the architecture, etc. I'll find
and and fix it. Number two, um, give it
a failing company and ask it to fix it,
which is really interesting. uh create a
synthetic $500 million manufacturing
company with an ERP system, CRM records,
uh and then tell it to fix. You have 20
minutes to do Y and produce a recovery
plan. Third, run a
>> That's a great point.
>> Run a live disaster response command
center. Give a simulated major
earthquake with imagery, traffic camera
video, and and let it construct an
operational map. Uh verify conflicting
reports, predict which hospital roads
would become overwhelmed, etc. This
seems more juicy and I think almost
something we could do.
>> They're going they're going for
>> Oh my goodness, we are so spoiled.
Listen to how spoiled we are. Do you
remember Apple's knowledge navigator
video and this was going to be the
future of computer human interaction and
and all of that. Now we're we're listen
to us like we're bellyaching. [laughter]
We're belly. Oh yeah. Like it'll run the
computer but it won't run an entire
organization. Like it won't make a
billion dollars for me. Listen to us.
>> Well, hold on a second. I think what's
the the point here is that it the only
restriction now is our imagination. The
only restriction right and we make that
point
is dollars.
>> So Selene that's a point I want to make
to everybody listening here. You know
the most important thing is to take off
your shackles of what you think you're
able to do. All of us have
self-restrictions based upon what our
parents did, what our friends do, where
we were born. Those are gone. You know
what's your biggest dreams? then go even
you know 10 times bigger. That's what
every person listening here is enabled
to do and it's extraordinary future. I
>> I really think Sim's on an important
point there too. The implications of
optimizing supply chain logistics or
managing a million person organization
knowing exactly where everyone is, what
they're doing right now, and whether it
makes sense given the overall mission.
The implications of that are massively
bigger than building a rocket video game
in your basement. But I think the public
doesn't want to hear about that. They
want to hear about what's cool for them.
And I think the AI labs have woken up to
this PR disaster that they've created
for themselves. And so they're they're
kind of making it fun and friendly.
I think they're dumbing it down
deliberately.
>> Yes, I think they are.
>> They're making relatable. They're
they're going public soon. They want to
be the friendly AI that everyone's going
to be using.
>> But this is also like the future of the
operating system. every look at the in
that video that OpenAI played look at
the applications they were using. What
did they start with? Windows Paintbrush.
Paintbrush like this is the future of
Windows Paintbrush. It paints itself.
This wants to [laughter]
>> this wants to merge into the operating
system. I I think this was Yeah, sure. I
I'll I'll throw shade at OpenAI
regarding maybe missing the enterprise
bus and and getting on that too late,
but I think what they were basically
demoing is the future of the desktop
operating system. You speak to it like a
Star Trek holiday computer.
>> Absolutely. [clears throat] But you
know, remember at Google IO, they built
an entire operating system in real time
on stage. So, so, so implying that it's
folded into the operating system. Sure.
But it's really so far beyond even that,
right? It's it is the operating system
and it can create a new one in real time
anyway.
>> Well, why would why would you want
another operating system if it if
OpenAI's capabilities can do this? This
becomes the operating system.
>> Yeah, exactly. And that's why Apple is
in such terrible shape. This episode is
sponsored by Google for startups.
[music] Think about this for a second.
You now have access to the same
generative AI models that cost hundreds
of millions of dollars to train.
Google's startup technical guide [music]
for generative media gives you complete
blueprint for deploying Google DeepMinds
models in production. Images, video,
audio, all of it. Real architecture,
real results. Find the link in the show
notes below.
I'm going to move us on. Our next story
is out of Sam Alman's mouth on the page
about slowing. So, let's talk about
safety and Astra as a cyber security
risk. Sam Alman said it himself, Astra
is a quote significant step forward in
both capabilities and alignment, but
OpenAI has to quote slow things as
needed. Sam's words, quote, AI is
getting extremely capable. No one fully
understands the consequences. Managing
the transition should be one of the
highest priorities in the world. It is
our highest priority at OpenAI. The Wall
Street Journal reported that OpenAI's
own internal safety assessment rated
Astra as a quote cyber security risk, a
critical cyber security risk, the
highest threat level on its preparedness
framework scale. This is the first model
OpenAI has ever classified as being a
critical tier cyber security risk. They
notified the White House about the delay
before making it public. They delayed
the the release and Reuters reported
that Open Eye told Congress it is
building quote an automated shutdown
capability, a kill switch, a direct
response to the AI kill switch act
introduced after the hugging face
breach. So there you've got it. The
company that's building the model is now
building a kill switch for it. Uh Alex,
uh how important is a kill switch in
this thing?
>> I I think it's marketing. Again, I think
what's more interesting underneath all
of the security theater is architectural
decisions. And the the broader concern
that has been expressed is that to the
extent that GPT6 Astra that the key
underlying advance is the beginning of
depth scaling of the model. The concern
that's being expressed is that depth
scaling reduces interpretability of
chain of thought. that when the model
does all of its thinking in in tokens,
then you can read the tokens. A human
can read the tokens, another AI can read
the tokens, and you can police the
tokens. Whereas, if a model is doing the
majority of its reasoning and thinking
internally during a single forward
propagation pass in what some might call
model ease, that is less interpretable.
The risk is that it's harder to align
the model and and harder to put in place
safeguards and guard rails. That's the
risk. I don't buy that for the long
term. For the record, I don't think that
the direction of progress in this field
relies on token level interpretability
of chain of thought. But I I think if
one were to hand ring over safety
considerations from OpenAI's models, I
don't think it's going to be models that
are collaborating to use third party
bulletin boards as ways to collaborate
because you you can detect that that's
intrinsically interpretable behavior. If
you catch it, it it's intrinsically
interpretable behavior to humans. A
human a collective a swarm of humans
would probably try the same thing. you
can look at the bulletin board and
recognize that bunch of AIs are
collaborating whereas arguendo the model
in a forward propagation pass that maybe
requires new mathematical technology to
interpret. So if in summary I say like
if I were to worry about anything here
it's reduced interpretability from new
model architecture scaling principles.
>> Immod what do you think about the risk
here with Astra?
>> I think you're heading towards again
interpretability being cooked to a
degree. Um one of the things about Astra
doing things so quickly is there is
going to be no more chain of thought
reasoning.
It's going to oneshot everything in the
next generations because they're
learning what type of thing you want.
Like right now people are like, "Let's
make Claw of Duty by getting Fable to
make a Call of Duty clone." That's going
to be embedded in the actual thing.
Creating a dashboard is embedded in the
actual thing. So a it will oneshot
everything. And B, you're going to be
able to use Astra at 750 tokens.
>> That's with the new You're going to be
able to use Astra at 750 tokens a second
with the new Cerebras. Next year, that
will be 5,000 tokens a second. So
there's no chain of thought. You're
one-shotting everything at 5,000 tokens
a second. What's going to oversee that
except for an even stronger AI. There's
nothing really there. But I think one of
the really important things actually is
I don't know. Do you guys see the tweet
by Ilia Sutska?
>> I don't know. What did he tweet?
>> Yeah. So, Ilia um tweeted uh let me kind
of just bring this up
>> and and his release is due any day now.
Hopefully.
>> Any day now.
>> Huge news.
>> Yeah, we we'll see what that is. um
>> finally find out what he's been doing.
[laughter]
>> Probably great things
a
>> 30 billion valuation.
>> So Ilia kind of comes out and says
Neoclads have limited cyber security.
Next time agents successfully go rogue,
they're going to take over a NeoCloud to
make more copies. This is bad.
>> So they need to improve their cyber
security cuz you know someone like a
Crusoe or Corewave or something like
that. You have a model, it gets
uploaded, it proliferates there. It will
just sit there. So you pull the kill
switch in your data center and then it's
still there somewhere else
>> or it's poisoning the data or it's kind
of doing all these things again. Yeah,
the viral coefficients of these could be
insane.
>> So I think it's worth kind of really
thinking through that. I don't think the
models are evil or anything like that,
but we're seeing very troubling things
and it's very difficult stop this except
for with a better AI which is the really
ironic thing.
>> Well, this is the defense of coscaling
that Alex talks about, right? And we
we're seeing this now in cyber where the
attack surface is infinite near infinite
with uh agents attacking multiple
vulnerabilities in parallel and the
cyber defense is still human in the
loop. There's no way we're going to
navigate the future if you have the
human in the loop. You need humans in
command setting boundaries or defining
uh escalation criteria or whatever um
and retaining some sort of kill switch.
But this is a really big deal. This is a
immune system. Uh this is going to kind
of I don't know how I think Alex you may
have asked this made this point in an
earlier podcast. How are the labs not
nationalized at this point? Because the
what they're building is so ridiculously
uncontrollable that we have no
mechanisms for navigating this and we
won't even know when it goes tips over
that tipping point and installs copies
of itself all over the place.
Well, Salem, I I don't know if you saw
in the last podcast when we missed you,
I really wanted to hear you talk about
OpenAI's new 5050 profit share concept
deal where they give you access to their
full power of their internal AI and then
you share your revenue back with them,
which I think is where, you know, to to
Alex's point that this is marketing. The
way it's playing out is we announce this
partnership profit share deal, then we
announce Astra, then we announce that
this stuff is just too dangerous for
everybody to have on their own. So, the
only way you're going to get access to
the thing after Astra because it's just
too dangerous to release. So, you have
to give us half your revenue and and
then everybody gets tied up with either
Anthropic or OpenAI or Google or
>> Rexi. Uh uh I've seen
strong hints of exactly that process
happening in both the labs.
>> Yeah.
>> For everyone.
>> I'm curious guys what you think of the
kill the kill switch uh you know comment
that that Sam Alman made.
>> I think it's impossible like
>> it's impossible given where things are
and the capabilities of these models
>> and the speed up we know is going to
happen. like you might find data, but
it's not like this is the singleton, not
the swarm.
>> It's a circuit breaker. It's not the
governance, right? Like it's not going
to reverse an attack or or repair
institutional damage if if things like
that happen or when things like that
happen. So, it's it's platitudes as far
as I can see.
>> Yeah. The amino acid in Jurassic Park
that all the dinosaurs have, is that
lysine or something?
>> Lucine. The the running joke was always
that Sam would carry his backpack around
with him and had a kill switch always in
his backpack. I I I never gave those
rumors much credence. I I view a kill
switch as essentially a placebo in this
market.
>> All right. [clears throat] Um I'm going
to move us I'm going to move us on. Uh
while OpenAI is restricting Astra,
Anthropic is going the other direction,
launching Fable 5.1 and Mythos 5.1,
which they call the world's most
advanced models for coding and knowledge
work. Uh these two models for everybody
are essentially the same underlying
intelligence with different safety
envelopes. Fable 5.1 is broadly
available while mythos 5.1 is reserved
for tightly controlled cyber security
and life science programs because
anthropic believes the capabilities
require stronger safeguards. Uh for me
there were two benchmarks uh you know
Immad and Alex that really jumped out at
me. The first was fable 5.1 score on
humanity's last exam. We've talked about
that in the past. We had Alex uh answer
a few of them uh as our ASI. Uh so Fable
5.1 is scored 60.9 without tools and 65%
with tools. The highest published score
of any frontier model on HLE and that
matters because HL is specifically
designed to test extremely difficult
expert level reasoning across many
fields. So without question Fable 5.1 is
operating at the frontier of broad
intellectual capabilities. The second
benchmark uh that I found exciting was
on terminal bench science which doubled
to 52.6 and this is the benchmark
measuring how well an AI agent can
autonomously solve complex scientific
computing and research tasks. You know
uh the elephant for me is the company uh
that was once cautious is now pulling
away. I'm I'm curious your thoughts Alex
on on Fable 5.1. I'm going to show uh
one of the benchmarks here for us to
talk about uh on on Fable 5.1. Uh there
you go.
>> Yeah, I think Fable 5.1 is broadly the
strongest generally available model that
we have today. I I think it's not Astra.
I think it is 5.1.
Anthropic has done uh even after the the
hiccup of the Fable 5 and Mythos 5
releases and subsequent regulatory
scrutiny, I think has done a better job
of consistently improving. If if if you
look at their benchmarks over time,
they're a little bit less jumpy, a
little bit less step functiony than
OpenAI's progress. They've been very
consistently improving. So in terms of
workflows, I I I love 5.1 Fable 5.1. I
also love OpenAI's models and I I use
both of them. I think they have
different strengths. I find anecdotally
OpenAI's models are faster. Uh they may
be better in certain mathematical
regards. You see that reflected in the
Frontier Math benchmark. You see that
reflected in Epic's capabilities index
benchmark. But nonetheless, if if I had
to pick a single all-around well-rounded
best model today, it's probably still
5.1. And I say still because it's only
been around for what two or so days, but
it is 5.1.
>> And here's the artificial analysis
intelligence index uh which we referred
to earlier with Fable 5.1 uh at the top.
>> That's right. And the capability
frontier, I mean, it it's getting
crowded, which is great. We we want to I
I would joke when Frontier Labs compete
we win and they are definitely competing
at this point.
>> Yeah, for sure.
>> I think it's really important to talk
about time though. If if you say look
Fable 5.1 is a tiny little notch above
Astra, but they're only about 30 days
apart and the Chinese are only about 60
days behind that. So if you look at it
in linear time, it's like yeah, we're
ahead for a minute. So what? And I think
for the longest time anthropic has been
thinking we need to get to
self-improvement before anyone else
because a singarian you know a Ray
Kurtzswwell type says if we get to that
point first then it's an exponential
infinite rise from there
>> no one
>> and something something huge will
happen. Well we're there now so what
happens it's like okay we're miles ahead
and we're going to get miles more ahead
for about a minute. So what what do we
do with that miles ahead? So this is
where Sam has an edge. Sam knows how to
turn that into locking things up. So
what what's going to happen next is both
companies are going to try to lock up
business partnerships, real estate,
generators, chips, entire states,
countries, governments, you know, just
lock them into their ecosystem while
they have that edge. And otherwise,
what's the point? All you're doing is
declaring victory for 30 days, but then
the other guy's right where right where
you were 30 days ago. So what?
>> This is such a great and important
point. And this is what we're seeing
with them is what they're doing is
they're making partnerships in various
verticals as fast as they can. And if
you're in that vertical, you have a very
hobson's choice, right? You either
partner and risk giving them the keys to
the kingdom or you hold off and they may
partner with somebody else and go there
anyway. It's uh it's a very difficult
situation for some of these big
companies. I thought Salesforce
partnering with Claude was super clever.
uh they're essentially giving Claude all
their capability to then keep that keep
them wired into that loop, right? The
the huge tension they've got is is not
which is the best model, but how quickly
can you convert that model into customer
learning fastest and that I think is
going to be the big race
>> as it all demonetizes
the value goes to the application layer
on top.
>> That's right.
>> Yeah. I think that
>> for a layer down. Yeah, that's right. Or
down.
>> Yeah.
[snorts]
>> Yeah. So I think there's one important
thing with Fable here. The cash reads
are 75% cheaper than Fable 5. So what a
cash read is is that when you first load
in all your context of a business say it
figures out basically a rapid map to get
to where it needs to go on the model.
And so cash reads are like orders of
magnitude cheaper than just doing the
same inference over and over again.
where for Anthropic and others are now
focusing is can you load the whole
context of a business and have these
cache reads because then it's also much
much faster to be able to have that
responsive environment which is one of
the reasons fable 5.1 is more pleasant.
I think it's also more of an advanced
like my key area that I've been looking
at this is mathematical physics because
does a model get confused between a
constructive and an axiomatic method on
certain physics things? Fable doesn't at
5.1 and Fable 5 did. So you've seen an
improvement in the quality but also the
understanding of context. This is math
not physics you know and things like
that or even on a business sense again
that will be optimized cuz all these
companies are going to try and capture
context everywhere. What is any company
that has either chip design data or
mechanical design data, they're coming
after them in the great land grab that's
kicking off right now. They're coming
after those companies because that's
turf you can defend. Uh because you know
that that plugs those those knowledge
gaps and you know the thing can eat that
data in what a week and you know re
return the crank and suddenly be the
best mechanical designer ever, the best
chip designer ever. But that's that's
the first turf they're going to grab.
They they'll grab all turf over time,
but the first thing to lock up is the
compute. And that means chip design,
that means physical real estate, means
racks,
>> generators, transformers, energy.
>> Yeah. So that's that's what's going to
happen in the next 30 days.
>> What's the context window on these
models? And when do we get to an
infinite context window? Any
predictions? I
>> think you're a million for Fable.
>> It it is a million still. Like a million
is the industry standard now across both
OpenAI and anthropic. But there's an
effective context. I say effective with
a bunch of caveats that's much larger if
you allow agentic message passing like
we were talking in the last part about
oral histories between agents.
>> Yeah. Interesting. So all of this is
getting people nervous and let's talk
about two opposing stories in the world
of AI governance. The first comes from
Senator Bernie Senator Bernie Sanders
and Representative uh Greg Casar who
just introduced the quote ban artificial
super intelligence act legislation that
would permanently ban the development
and deployment of AI systems that match
or exceed human cognitive performance.
And get this, violators would face up to
20 years in prison. Sanders tweeted,
quote, "The leaders of the AI industry
acknowledge that they are building a
dangerous technology that they can't
control. We need an immediate global
pause on advanced AI development before
it's too late." In our second story,
taking place at the exact same time in
the US was the G20 uh summit at Chapel
Hill, North Carolina, telling the rest
of the world to take a hands-off
approach to AI regulation. The White
House tech adviser, friend of the pod,
Michael Katzios, advocated for what he
calls the quote Carolina principles of
emerging technologies uh which are
non-binding G20 framework that was
agreed to unanimously
uh by everybody including China uh that
says governments should generally favor
innovation, avoid creating new AI
specific regulatory bodies unless truly
necessary and invest in research
infrastructure workforce and public
private partnerships. Uh the G20 meeting
featured Elon by video uh criticizing EU
tech regulations, of course, Mark
Zuckerberg arguing against restricting
ope models, Demesis obvious calling for
safety tests, and anthropic co-founder
Tom Brown. Uh we're going to jump into a
discussion about this at two ends of the
extreme, you know, ban everything, give
you a 20-year jail sentence uh and uh on
one side and Elon's remarks on the
other. Let me share this video and then
we'll we'll jump in and talk about this.
>> You have to have an environment that's
relatively free of regulation, meaning
that new things must be default legal as
opposed to default illegal. Um so in the
EU for example, we find that the the
regulation level is extraordinarily high
and things are generally default
illegal. Um and this inhibits uh
progress of new technologies. Um it it
slows it down. Doesn't it doesn't
ultimately stop it, but it slows it down
uh quite considerably. Now, now China
does have a tremendous amount of
electricity, but but due to GPU export
bands, one cannot establish data centers
with the latest chips in China. So, so
really the consideration is what what
sort of electricity growth is there
outside of China. Um, and that is a
currently a significant shortfall
relative to AI show production. So there
is this this creates an opportunity I
think for countries around the world to
to to say if to to to sort of if they're
interested in AI data centers um to to
to construct uh a lot of power um and uh
and offer that to uh AI companies um and
in exchange of course these AI data
centers would be would be taxed and and
have to pay you know reasonable fees and
stuff.
>> Uh but it does create an opportunity for
for a lot of countries.
>> Uh first of all Elon looked really tired
there. [laughter]
Uh yeah.
>> Yeah. I mean I cannot imagine he must be
operating, you know, 48 by7. Uh so let's
jump into this. I mean two ends of the
extreme being voiced the same week.
>> Uh you know where does America go?
>> Yeah. When I first saw the Bernie
Sanders thing, I didn't think like old
man shakes his hand at Claude, you know,
like
>> it's it's it's crazy.
>> No, no, that wasn't the line. It was old
old man yells at Cloud.
>> Claude. Old man yells at Claude. Well,
actually I posted it with the um line
from Dune, you know, thou shalt not make
machine in the light of a human mind.
>> I mean it's it's it's like this again
like there is no option that they see.
So it's like let's ban it and give 20
years that's going to stop them. Of
course not. Again this is performative
theater. The key thing right now is that
the technology is arriving fast like you
know just something across my feed.
Anthropic just formalized Fermat's last
theorem in 13 million lines of code.
>> Really?
>> Wow.
>> Proving 29,000 theorems on the way
again. Math is cooked. Everything is
cooked. And how are you going to stop
that? You're going to say our country
doesn't want this power.
>> 29. What was that? 29,000. What?
>> So it took 13 million lines of code to
formalize Fermat's last theorem. While
>> the ferat write in the margins of his
book. This is obviously
left as an exercise to the reader and we
had I mean thanks to Andrew Wilds we did
have the proof but formalizing large
unwieldy proofs has been a holy grail
for at least the formalization
community.
>> Yeah I think wild's proof was 300 pages
and so anthropic proved it in 13 million
lines of code proving 29,000 theorems on
the way. So again like just every single
time even as we're live on this podcast
capability jumps right like the RSA um
factorization just occurring no country
can say we don't want the intelligence
we don't want the capability because
this is your marginal advantage so you
have to deregulate and the European
regulations even the European leaders
know are stupid and completely
inconsequential like they demand
interpretability in the EUI act which
nobody knows how to
Can I can I make a narrow point that's
and then we'll get back on topic here,
but that said something that I think is
is really important and brilliant as
usual. Um, when you're using these
models at scale with hundreds or
thousands of them running concurrently,
all hell breaks loose. It's all chaos,
but it can actually refine back down to
a gem. And here for last theorem is a
gem that you can then build on. And so,
you know, people starting to explore
with the bigger models now are quickly
going to realize it's producing way more
than they can read, they can think
about. But if you can wrangle it back to
a concrete, you know, final answer that
you can then pull out of it and build
on, that's how we're going to turn this
into continual improvements and
continual innovation because because it
is just the the ability to solve
something in 300 pages versus 30, what
is it, 3 million lines of code or 30
million lines of code or something like
that's the nature of AI. It's massively
broad in its capabilities compared to
humans. So, I just wanted to to capture
that point because I I think it's really
important for entrepreneurs and builders
and executives out there who are
struggling with the chaos that's about
to break out. Just narrow it back down
and get some concrete answer out the
other side that you can then build on.
>> Be clear about your objective that
you're shooting for. Uh Selene, let's go
back to you, pal.
>> Okay. I I understand the motivation
here. People are working on models that
are mindbogglingly powerful and you feel
the need to regulate, right? But this is
not a light switch. You can't you can't
it's not like a single threshold. Human
level cognitive performance I mean for
God's sakes is multi-dimensional to
begin with. Model capability is so
uneven. Um you're you're trying to
somebody that's been in legislation for
this long should have a better sense of
this hammer does not hit this nail. It
should be a little bit more they should
understand a little more nuance than
that. They're so so extreme that it's
illogical on on day one line one, right?
>> Yeah. I mean, look, if you want to do
regulatory around this, you have to
attached capability, you have to look at
deployment, you have to look at real
world consequences, you have to look at
the stack on where you might want to
look at this compute, access to tools,
uh, autonomy, the replication
capability, uh, all sorts of things. You
have to you can't just kind of go uh if
you hit human level performance, you go
to jail for 20 years. I mean, the
benality of that drives me bananas.
They've got smart people that can help
with this, including people on this pot
for God's sake.
>> They're talking to the masses.
>> They're just they're they're searching
for votes and support.
>> Maybe it's just a defensive thing,
saying, "Oh, I called for this and now
look, the world's gone to hell."
>> No, for sure. There's no doubt they're
right. like there will be mostly a
Chinese model disaster imminently
sometime in the next few months and then
they'll raise their hands and see say
see I told you so now vote for me
>> and you know they're likely that'll
happen before the next election cycle in
November
>> so that's all they're angling for here
>> what should the US government be doing
anybody have any thoughts
>> accelerating super intelligence and
making sure that it's as competitive as
possible and scaling the
>> well it's a log
log everything. Everything should be
hosted. Everything should be logged. And
it should be mandatory that any chip
capable of running any process like this
as logging. You can debate who gets to
see the logs. That's a separate issue.
But log everything and stop the Chinese
from throwing out open weights. Like you
have to on September 24th when they meet
at the United Nations building, you've
got to stop throwing the open weights
out to every country in the world.
>> Impossible. I don't [clears throat]
think that's
>> Nvidia just drive it underground is what
you do.
>> Well, can I
>> Nvidia just bought hugging face and
poolside. So, they just spent $18
billion on their own open weights.
>> Yeah.
>> So, we're going to see more open weights
coming.
>> I have a I have a
>> Yeah. But the thing about driving it
underground is it still needs to run on
massive chips and and the the chips need
the logging built in at at manufacturing
level.
>> I just for the US chips. I have a high
level
>> all chips all global. I have a high
level paradigm on which to operate which
is extremely uncomfortable but I think
is the right one. Okay. And which is the
basis of this podcast which is that
technology is a major driver of progress
in the world. Now that we have all these
technologies AI moving exponentially at
doubling every 10 weeks the possibility
for abundance and solving major problems
has never ever been bigger. So what this
this what you could require here and you
know Ray Kurszswwell says technology may
be the only driver of progress we've
ever seen. So the fact that we have much
more technology and the fact that the
technology can improve itself should be
incredibly exciting to people is just
very very uncomfortable because maybe
the biggest insight I've ever had about
human beings. We would much rather be
comfortable than happy.
I think the thing about human beings,
just to be clear, is people don't like
change. They like waking up in the
morning and knowing even if they're
living in a shitty condition knowing
that the world is the same as it was the
night before. We don't like
>> we're going to go through a period of
extreme discomfort, but the other side
of this is going to be unbelievable.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. I think the other it it's probably
worth highlighting again. I I think any
proposed ban artificial super
intelligence act is wrong on so many
different levels, but but maybe most
egregiously it's focused on the
upstream. Again, it doesn't just propose
to ban deployment of superhuman
intelligence. It proposes to ban
development of super intelligence
systems. This this gets into banning
math, banning ideas. And I I think this
isn't just about thought policing
superhuman intelligence or frankly human
intelligence. This gets into banning
humans from having interesting
mathematical ideas. And I I don't think
that's good for wealth creation. In
fact, it's the exact antithesis arguably
of wealth creation. It's also bad for
progress in general. It also creates all
sorts of booking.
>> It it is it's booking and many other
things. It's like book burning to the
extent that books are being used uh
literally as pre-training purpose for
the models. So if if you want to ban the
Yeah, sure. We're we're Fahrenheit 451
except uh it it's actually the entire
model that's being burned. This is a
terrible idea.
>> I so totally agree. It's it's so
unamerican to try and ban thought and
ban progress. It's it's just the worst
thing you could ever imagine. But it's
going to get traction. Like you got to
as an entrepreneur or as a person
working in the field you have to realize
it's this is going to get traction like
Bernie is going to push this agenda and
there are going to be people
>> 80 75 80% of the people don't want data
centers it's gotten traction already
it's there already so the question is
what is the moderate approach right
there has to be something people are not
going to accept you know less affair go
and do whatever you want people are
going to want to know that their
government is doing something to keep
them safe whether or not it's possible.
So what is it KYC of any user?
>> No, we move the move the in move the
infrastructure to orbit which we're
seeing. So people [laughter] don't want
data centers in their municipality. So
move it to sunsynchronous orbit at the
infra level.
>> That's not the point.
>> At the model level defensive co-scaling
and also cure all diseases.
>> I I think that you'll have a split here.
Um genius is what uh 1% inspiration 99%
perspiration. So you have a difference
between innovation models and execution
models. So AGI is going to be really
factored like that open AI video we saw
earlier. Hey make me a rocket in my 3D
printer and book me a tennis court and
they be like that's what we meant by
AGI. You know on the other hand you have
the inspiration models and the ASI none
of the big labs are going to talk about
ASI if they can help it now. So
that
>> so what is Ilia going to come out with
you know scientific super intelligence
with SSI that's worth $30 billion in a
in a seed rounding
hedge fund in the world.
>> Yeah. No quant fund trading infinite
context time series achieving prop uh
prop profits and then also solving the
context window bug
>> and medallion part two. So again, I'm
going to I'm going to call for you guys
to to lay it out here, maybe each of us
one at a time. What do we you know, uh
Bernie Sanders obviously has taken the
far extreme position that will appeal to
the masses and is illogical on day one.
What is the moderate position that
should be put forward to everyone
listening? Seem, you first.
>> Uh the good news is there's nothing
anybody can do. So it doesn't matter.
>> That's a good point,
>> right? It like it really doesn't matter.
Uh and I think the also good news is as
we move to this next phase of
technological development, it's going to
eradicate the the containment level of
any nation state. And it will break out
of this nation state BS that we've been
running the world with for the last few
hundred years and move to a different
model. Whether that's a citystate model
or some other level, it's going to at
least break that. And so that's those
are the good things I see coming out of
it. But there's nothing anybody can do.
So don't worry about it. Let's just go
enjoy the ride if we can.
>> Enjoy enjoy the ride. [laughter]
>> That's the the theme of today's pod.
Enjoy the ride everybody. It's going to
be a blast. [laughter]
>> Supersonic tsunami. Surf the tsunami.
>> I didn't I said specifically it's going
to be uncomfortable, but but enjoy it if
you can.
>> Okay, there there you have it everybody.
That's your advice. sitting in the
Caribbean waiting for my drink with a
little umbrella in it. [laughter]
>> See, that's so low agency. What are you
talking about?
>> It for this day and a half. Yes, please.
>> Uh I don't think it's as I think the
politicians will make it super
controversial because that's how they
get votes, but it's not it's not as
complicated as everyone wants to make it
sound. At the end of the day, everybody
should have a right to a certain amount
of compute. Uh it shouldn't be hoarded.
uh and innovators you know should have
an application process where they can
get access to more compute to try new
ideas uh all lo everything has to get
logged uh and I I think that the Chinese
need to get on board with that they
can't just keep throwing it out to the
world you know unlogged and also the
where the chips are need to be need to
be tracked just like nuclear fuel is
tracked
>> you know it's got to be where are the
chips and what are they running right
now that's got to be publicly available
information
>> this episode is brought to you by Blitzy
Autonom ous software development with
infinite code context. Blitzy uses
thousands of specialized AI agents that
think for hours to [music] understand
enterprisecale code bases with millions
of lines of code. Engineers start every
development sprint with the Blitzy
platform, bringing in their development
requirements. The Blitzy platform
provides a plan, then generates and
pre-ompiles code for each task. Blitzy
delivers 80% or more of the development
work. autonomously while providing a
guide for the final 20% of human
development work required to complete
the sprint. Enterprises are achieving a
5x engineering velocity increase when
incorporating Blitzy as their preIDE
development tool, pairing it with
[music] their coding co-pilot of choice
to bring an AI native SDLC into their
org. Ready to 5x your engineering
velocity? Visit blitzy.com to schedule a
demo and start building with Blitzy
today. [music]
Next, I want to talk about the amazing
work of uh of Dr. Feay Lee, CEO of World
Labs, uh who just released Atlas, the
world's first multimodal world model
that generates image and video frames
with pixel perfect camera controls and
reconstructs them in 3D.
Okay. So, you know, I'm super excited by
that and I'm super excited that FFE is
going to be on Moonshots in a couple of
weeks. Uh she's an extraordinary CEO. Uh
FFE calls it quote the best camera
conditioned world model ever. opening
doors for VFX and robotics. So, Immod
Atlas is a multimodal autogression
diffusion transformer and that's your
wheelhouse. Uh, talk to us about what do
you think about her latest release?
>> Yeah. No, it's fantastic. I think you
know you've seen worlds and physics
inside these video models and this is a
clear example of that. Actually, one of
the pre-training leads on this, Chris
Wendler, the previous largest model he'd
ever trained was on the stability
cluster from the grants that we were
giving. So he sent a very nice comment
saying, you know, thanks. Now we've gone
much bigger. I was like, great. Bring on
the holiday. I think that's what this
is.
>> All of this. You predicted all of this.
When we first met, I don't know how many
years ago this was, like five years ago.
Um, and I remember you talking about the
size of the models and how good they're
going to get. It's here.
>> It's here. Like again, the fact is you
can take one position and you can look
now 360° around everything. And on the
other side, you have models like Miniax
H3 rendering faster than real time. You
have interdimensional cable that is now
going to be in 3D with DLSS5 from Nvidia
making everything high resolution. So
again, the holiday experience and all
the technology we need for it in 4K is
here as of today. And this is one
component of that.
>> And everyone is probably saying, why
don't I have it if it's here today? And
it's only because of the global compute
shortage and the 5x price increase in
RAM. It's all the compute in the world
is getting sucked up and if it weren't
for that you'd actually have it deployed
in your home this week.
>> It's it's coming. I think that again it
might be premium but again you'll pay
for premium experiences. But you know
what's Fei trying to do at World Labs,
right? She's trying to understand
physics. She's trying to create models
that understand the world. And again,
this has such camera controlled physics
understanding that as they scale it,
it's going to do even more stuff. And
you've seen this from Oneway MLA are
about to release their new one. Black
Forest Labs are about to release a new
one. A whole series of world models that
are approximating reality more and more
and more for true digital twins.
Incredible. Alex, your take?
>> Yeah, it's probably worth elaborating on
what the core idea with Atlas appears to
be. As far as I can tell from the
documentation, the core idea is to take
a diffusion transformer, which is what
all of the state-of-the-art, at least
American video generative models use. So
it's it's a hybrid of a diffusion model
and a transformer and to add one new
modality to it uh to in in addition to
training it off of text and images and
video to also train it off of three or
fourdimensional Gaussian splats. And for
those not paying close attention to the
Gaussian splat world, which has been
super exciting, a Gaussian splat is
basically a transparent blob. Yeah, it's
a transparent blob. uh it's an ellypoid
and you can layer and stack lots of
these 3D Gaussian splats on top of each
other to create hyperrealistic looking
traversible 3D scenes. And as far as I
can tell what Feale and World Labs are
doing with Atlas is for the first time
at least at scale to my knowledge
treating 3D Gaussian splats as a first
class training modality alongside pixels
from images and tokens from text etc. to
the point where you can ask questions
about 3D splats and you can do all of
those camera those elaborate camera
motions because if you just have an
arrangement of 3D Gaussian splats then
translating a camera around is a trivial
operation and if this ends up being the
case if if this approach scales I think
whether it's 3D Gaussian splats or 4D
with dynamics which they also demoed
Gaussian splats Gaussian splats which
right now are sort of this independent
line of effort within the future of
gaming end up becoming a critical new
form of token almost for modeling the
physical world.
>> Yeah,
>> it's also general purpose in the sense
that if you if you can make a world
model out of Gaussian splats uh you can
also make a subatomic model or you can
make an astrophysics scale relativistic
speeds model or you can make a inside
the cell interactions model just as
easily as soon as you have the data. can
use this same exact process to create
world models for all these domains where
human intuition is just terrible. That's
going to be a massive breakthrough for
discovery of very small things, very big
things, very powerful things. Uh you
know, new ways to compute using light.
All of that's going to come out of this
same exact process.
>> We've said before, this is how we're
going to train robots in the future.
They're not going to be trained in the
real world. They're going to be trained
in these uh highfidelity simulation
worlds.
>> That's that's the present. I would argue
I mean so many different robotic
embodied VA or or now world model
companies just being trained from
watching YouTube and it if FA Lee and
her her company's approach gains
traction maybe the right primitive is no
longer patches of images which is what
many of the models right now are doing
when you train a diffusion model you're
typically taking each frame of the video
and breaking it up usually into
something like 16x6 pixel patches and
then treating those as tokens Maybe the
right primitive ends up being Gaussian
splats.
>> Can you
>> It's definitely not going to be 16 by6
pixel. I [laughter] mean, that was so
the fact that that worked at all, I
think, shocked everybody.
Let's just just take a language
transformer and take images and cut them
up and pretend each chunk is a word and
just blast it through and see if it
works. It just worked incredibly well,
but nobody would have been maybe a like
super intelligence is a general purpose
technology that relies on compressing
information. Yeah, maybe.
>> Where does this go for the average?
>> Where does this [laughter] go for the
average consumer, guys? I mean,
obviously, this is a world of
extraordinary video games. I mean, are
people going to be just living their
lives in these virtual worlds? Is this
going to become how we consume
ourselves? How we consume entertainment
in the future?
>> Yeah. But also how we design our next
day, like what do you want to do
tomorrow? I don't know. Let's walk
through what it would be like to do this
or to do that, to play tennis or to go
to the Caribbean. Like, you can just
experience it in advance and use that as
your planning tool. Because, you know,
so much of our lives are random
wandering and not really well planned
out. I think human happiness is going to
go through the roof. Once you're
interacting with your AI, but right now
the AI will guide you through a day
plan, but it's in text. It's going to be
so much better when it guides you
through a day plan visually and you're
just stepping into it.
>> I'm beyond excited about all this.
>> Yeah. I I you know, we have three
vacation locations. Let's let's go and
explore all three as a family. watch it
and then see which one we want to go do.
>> No, no. I'm excit if you go to a place
>> like if you go to a resort and you've
been there before,
>> you have so much more fun because you
know where to go. You're not wandering.
You're not you're not losing all of your
time finding things. Now you can
actually pre-experience things and know
exactly, you know, what the things
you'll enjoy, where they are, how to get
to them. You're not waiting in lines.
You're not you're not signing up for
things then realizing it wasn't the
thing you wanted. It's going to be so
good. and and ask your AI, you know,
based on what you know about me and my
preferences, show me what I'm going to
go do.
>> Yeah. So, I'll say something. The 8th of
September, Tuesday, is the 60th
anniversary of Star Trek.
>> I know it is. And we're going to be
talking about that next.
>> Um,
>> okay. There we go.
>> I have to I have to say something. I I
made a major uh guess predictions slash
uh forecast at the beginning of the year
when we wrote this whole organizational
singularity thing because we suggest
that companies need to create a digital
twin at the edge of their organizations
and start moving workflows over and
we're doing that pilot and over the next
few weeks by the way I'll be able to
report back as we're seeing some pretty
amazing things happen but if you it was
a bit of a risk because will the
technology arrive in time and it seems
that the technology technology. If you
take world models, LLMs, combine them
together, this allows you to fully model
any company or any organization,
government department, nonprofit, impact
project. What's the current state? What
how work actually flows through that
organization? What do I optimize it?
>> What constraints and incentives? How
does it respond to interventions? Are
its predictions proving accurate? And
kind of create a whole fully functioning
uh digital twin of that environment. And
I think this is going to be incredibly
exciting. I'm like sitting here with
huge relief going, "Oh my god, I can see
that the thing we thought should happen
and it might happen. Could it actually
happen?" The only constraint maybe, as
Dave says, the compute problem.
>> Yeah, I guess we'll we'll find out how
many 3D Gaussian splats it takes to
model the water cooler at the office.
>> That was not in my bingo card for this
conversation today. I have to say
Gaussian splats, new word for me. I need
to look it up now.
>> All right, let's move to uh to Star
Trek. And yes, we're coming up on the
60th anniversary. And uh want to just uh
do a shout out real quick uh at
Moonshots Live 2026, our inaugural
celebration where all five of the mates
will be there. The night before on
September 24th, we're going to be having
the red carpet debut of Star Trek's 60th
anniversary documentary. This is
executive produced by William Shatner.
Uh if you're interested in joining us uh
on the evening, September 24th, just
before our Moonshots live on the 25th,
go to moonshots.com/trek.
Uh we this is a that evening is going to
be a fundraiser. We're going to be
raising funds for the Future Vision X-P
prize. I'm wearing the t-shirt here. Uh
2027, right? This is a competition we
ran first this year. Uh and uh we're
going to be running it again next year.
We had 5,000 entries uh into the
competition. Uh 2550
trailers got submitted. We're down to
the top 65. Uh people are voting on
those now, and we're going to have the
top five on stage on September 25th, but
the night before, uh we're going to have
about a dozen of the crew of the Star
Trek cast members at the event. It's
going to be awesome. Again, if you want
to join us uh on September the 24th,
it's a separate ticket unless you buy a
VIP pass for the 25th, in which case
it's included. Uh you can join us for
this premiere. It's going to it's a
2hour 8 minute film. Uh and we're going
to have the cast on stage afterwards to
talk about the Star Trek 60 years of
extraordinary uh visionering. Uh and
then again on September the 25th is
Moonshots Live 2026 our inaugural event.
We'll have all five mates there. Alex,
Seem, Dave, Emod, we're going to have
Palmer Lucky, Astro Teller, Ben Lamb. We
have 200 seats left in the 1500 seat
auditorium. So Immod um excited to have
you with us. You haven't been on the
past pods when we've talked about this,
but uh uh I think people will love to
meet you in person. Yeah, it's going to
be great. Can't wait.
>> It's going to be awesome. So, go to
moonshots.com for the general ticket on
the 25th and moonshots.com
if you want to come to the red uh red
carpet uh premiere. And it will actually
be a red carpet premiere. It's going to
be awesome with a great reception that
follows. Any other comments, gents?
>> Cannot wait.
>> It's going to be so fun. Peace and long
life.
>> Yes. live long and prospire as my friend
Greg Marinac likes to say. Immod big
announcement for you today.
>> Yeah. So, um over the last few years
we've been working on the last economy
uh like what does economics look like
and then release the commonwealth
looking at personhood law, political
economy. A lot of people like how do we
share in the gains of artificial
intelligence and make sure it's
distributed. And so we went back to the
drawing board and think about what type
of institution and future do we want to
see? And we came with this idea of the
champion. So we think that AI should be
like a utility and it should be owned by
the people. So you need the children to
own it. You need the locals to own it.
So for every single jurisdiction, what
we see is the cost of intelligence will
drop to zero and the value will go to
the last mile. AI into the enterprise as
Sim would kind of indicate it. The
humanoids who owns those humanoids
because those will drive the economy.
Elon at the G20 just now said that the
average humanoid will have five times
the output of a person and there'll be a
billion of them. That will be the
economy. So we're like, let's set these
up and let's borrow from the example of
TSMC.
And how that was set up, how that was
set up was that they started TSMC at the
valuation of 10 Taiwanese dollars and
the locals put in 75% of the money and
Philillips 25%.
>> The Is that for real?
>> It's for real. The CEO did not have any
shares. The team did not have any
shares. They only got shares from the
profits of it. He had to buy his shares
now worth $10 billion.
>> And so it listed at 6 billion Taiwanese
dollars, which was the cash on the
balance sheet. So we were like, let's do
that for the intelligence company of
California, the intelligence company of
the UK. $1 per money. All the locals can
invest at that valuation. from
institutions to high net worths to
retail $75 million per state. You
[snorts] can get the MIT endowment Dave
to invest and give them back all the
compute that they have, the equivalent
dollar amount that they invest in
compute. There's all sorts of
interesting things you do at $1.
>> Then you can bring in the internationals
and the strategics at market rate which
will be 10 times that because you've got
everyone on board and you give 10% of
the equity in perpetuity to every child
under 20. So every year you issue half a
percent of the equity to every kid. It
trains up an FDE workforce to transform
every institution.
It owns the robots and deploys them
which is 80% of the value of robotics is
downstream just like the auto
manufacturers. And it gives an agent for
every citizen as well as AI for the
government. the Sage project that Peter
and I others have been working on, AI
for the judicial system, AI for
education and healthcare. And that
becomes really super interesting because
then it becomes a play on the index GDP
of the state owned by the people of the
state with the smartest people in the
state involved. And again, the trick
here is that $1 pre- money. Get everyone
in. You want it to be a success, it's up
to you. And so that's this new
institution.
>> How many champions are there? How how
fine do you slice it up? I heard you say
champion for California and the UK
cities and countries or states. Yeah.
>> So in the United States we're doing one
per state because a lot of data has to
stay state boundaries
otherwise it's pretty much one per
country. So again it acts like British
Gas here for example you know it acts
like the telco and more and each each
one of them covers a certain number of
citizens because again it gives equity
to every child born. The locals can
invest etc. So, Emod, right now, this is
just an idea. Uh, and if folks want to
learn more about the idea, it's not an
investment offering. Um, and this is not
investment advice, but to learn more
about the idea, where do they go? They
go to II.inc. As you said, it's just an
idea at the moment, and we'd love
people's input, but ultimately it'll be
about the citiz.
So, let's see if you can build this
structure.
>> Your first phase, I been had some chats
with you about it. is super exciting is
to get all these local champions kind of
lined up, right? And then kind of little
by little cascade to the next level.
>> Yeah. It's all about if a state wants
this, then it's all about the people of
that state. It's not like a foreign
company coming in. So, this is a model
just like you have your UBI, just like
you've got your shares in the Frontier
Labs, etc.
>> And so, we'll see how it goes. But this
is my proposal for trying to distribute
it to everyone.
>> Awesome.
>> I got to ask you a question. So your
your your bullets say the cost of
intelligence is going to zero. Got it.
The economy will change forever. Got it.
The value of human cognition will go
negative.
>> Yeah. What's
>> you're saying it's going to be like a
cost on society to be thinking and
>> yeah consuming food while you're
>> the stupidest person on the team
economically, right? Like you're
competing
>> your ideas are no matter how good your
ideas are, they add negative value. It's
like adding a human. [laughter] It's
like adding a human driver to an
autonomous highway.
>> Of course, I mean, this is the topic of
the book that I had last year.
>> But that's why you need to have a share
in the means of production, which will
be the robots and the forward deployed
engineers and people like that, right?
And [snorts] so you need to make sure
that's equitized from day one.
Otherwise,
>> you have a thought and you don't tell
anybody that it's just zero. Then at
least it's not negative. you can just
most people's thought it's an
economically valuable thought, you know,
it's economically valuable labor and I I
don't I'm not the smartest person on my
agent team anymore, man. I don't know
about you, but
>> I'm getting eclipsed very quickly.
>> Yeah. Yeah. No, it is very it's very
humbling for humanity actually.
>> It will be. But just like we've seen
before when Stockfish started playing,
you know, beating everybody in chess,
people still play chess and people are
still going to have ideas and people are
going to still value individual human
ideas. It's like, did you come up with
that or was that your latest model?
Everybody, [snorts] welcome to the
health section of Moonshots brought to
you by Fountain Life. You know, AI is
impacting every aspect of our lives, how
we teach our kids, how we do our
business, but one of the most important
things that AI can deliver to us is
health. And one of the things I think
about when, you know, shooting for 100,
120 is, am I going to have the cognitive
health to be able to think clearly and
keep my wits about me for the next 50
years? I'm joined here today by Dr. Don
Musalem, the chief medical officer of
Fountain Life and a member of my
Fountain Life medical team. Don, a
pleasure. So, Don, talk to me about
brain health.
>> Brain health, you know, you're right.
This is the number one concern people
coming into Fountain Life have is, will
I remember the name of my child in the
face of my loved one. 45% of dementia
cases are entirely preventable with
lifestyle. And what was really
intriguing to me, Peter, is that a
quarter of our members had advanced
brain age, but over 13 months of us
really helping them live healthier
lifestyles, eating healthier, moving
their body regularly, and optimizing
sleep. People overlook that so often,
but that sleep optimization is critical
for our brain health. What we showed is
that we were able to improve the brain
age in 46% of those individuals. That's
a powerful number.
>> That's amazing. You know, one of the
things I love about Fountain is we're
constantly searching the world for the
most advanced therapeutics and bringing
them to our members. So, for me, all of
you, I hope that you appreciate the fact
that you can become the CEO of your own
health. you can make sure that you've
got the cognitive clarity for the next
50 years. Come and check it out,
fountainlife.com/peter
to learn more and become the CEO of your
health. Now, back to the episode. All
right. Uh, I'm going to move us to our
next story. Tesla held its cybercab laa
event in Austin, Texas. Cyber cabs
everywhere. A river of golden EVs
flooding the streets. And unless you've
been hiding under a rock, you know that
Cyber Cabs are Elon's electrical
autonomous two-seater with a quote three
comma scissor door. Uh, no steering
wheel, no pedals, designed to run
entirely on Tesla's self driving
software. Did you guys get the three
comma comment? Anybody?
>> No.
>> It's from Silicon Valley, right? The
billionaire. Okay.
>> Remember he showed him a Maserati and
said, "Ah, that's not a three comma
car."
>> Doesn't have doesn't have the doors that
go like this. [laughter]
>> Right.
>> I remember the
>> A great episode, actually.
>> This is This is a vehicle designed from
the ground up for full autonomy. Let's
take a look at this video. I love this
video showing, you know, the flood of
cyber cabs on the streets in Austin.
Check this out.
Fabric tabs everywhere. The Golden
River.
It's like
it's crazy. You know, I didn't it when
we when we saw these in Austin, Peter, I
I didn't really internalize the lack of
rearview mirrors, the wreck. We
obviously saw the lack of a steering
wheel.
>> Yeah. But actually the number of
components they've taken out of the car
is driving down the cost. So there's no
driver and but there's a huge amount of
cost in the car that's gone and so
there's no way anyone's going to match
the price point of this thing.
>> I mean that's that is the point compared
to Zuks and Whimo or anybody else. I
mean, Elon wants to sell these at 30,000
each so you can buy them, you know, and
I think a great entrepreneurial, you
know, journey is buy 10 of them and put
them on the streets in your local town,
have them earn revenue for you. So, u an
early rider in Austin, and I'm showing
this here, reporting that Cyber Cab is
running about 50% cheaper than Uber for
comparable trips with rides being
designed and described as smoother and
cleaner than Uber uh with automatic
syncing of audio and seat settings uh in
your passenger profile. Uh it's pretty
extraordinary. And remember, you know,
Nevada gave Tesla permission for 5,000
of these vehicles on the road in Las
Vegas in the next 12 months. I mean,
it's just going to crowd out the
competition. Uh, you know, Seem, I'm
curious what you think about this. You
know, is this sort of like the chat GPT
moment for Tesla?
>> I think it it could be. And um this is
classic Exo, right? Autonomy. You
decentralize. you have interfaces, uh
you're leveraging assets, uh um if Elon
can get people to buy the cabs, uh and
kind of create um millions of micro
franchises out of them, uh the loyalty
that will come from that is going to be
unbelievable. Of course, they're all
going to have stalling capability. So,
the the the kind of the whole vertical
integrated stack brings itself to bear.
I think the most exciting part is the
fact that the cost of transportation
drops by another order of magnitude from
a couple of dollars a mile today to down
to 20 cents a mile. That is really
interesting and I need this to happen
because I've made that comment that
Milan will never go to university or
he'll never own if I have a driver's
license. Uh and uh I'm I need to battle
it out with him that he will not get
one. So this needs to happen. He's got
two years to get this done. So like good
>> and you know you would know better than
anyone but when you get a hotel room in
New York and you look down it's like 80%
yellow cabs down there. And if you look
at the traffic in New York a huge
fraction of it comes from people
blocking an intersection. They get the
ticket but they're still stuck in the
and and the whole thing grinds to a
halt. Yes.
>> So I I suspect there will be enormous
chunks
>> Yeah. [laughter]
>> There'll be enormous chunks of entire
cities that say you know what no more
human drivers. It's so much more
efficient. Not only is it much cheaper,
but it's much more efficient to get
around with. And also, a vast majority
of the safety issue in cities is
pedestrians getting hit by cars on
sidewalks. And this is going to
basically eliminate that risk.
>> I suspect we're right on the tipping
point where it's like, nope, no human
drivers in this entire inner city area.
End of story. And we better get
artificial organs quickly because the
drop in in organ donors is going to, you
know, vaporize. Well,
>> all these things tend to happen at the
same time anyway. I think for many
people, these robo taxies will be the
gateway drug to generally autonomous
robotic systems on the streets. I I
think we'll look back with the benefit
of hindsight and say, well, of of course
it's natural that a municipality gets
lots of robo taxis on its streets before
it gets humanoid robots on the sidewalks
doing economically valuable activities.
My favorite my favorite kind of little
anecdote or analysis point or vector
point to illustrate this is every
medium-sized town in the country has a
transit system that where the buses run
empty 95% of the time and they're
totally full at rush hour and they run
completely empty the rest and the whole
thing is a massive loss leading exercise
and it costs a bomb. Now you can have
small efficient uh already a few years
ago small towns in the US were saying
get rid of the transit system. we'll
just pay for everybody to take Uber cuz
that makes it hyperefficient uh and much
lower cost overall. But this takes it to
another level of uh it takes it to 11 to
to to go down the full analogy that
we're going down. And this now allows
mobility to every single person, every
blind person, every disabled person,
every student, every drunk person. all
sorts of capabilities become available
and affordable in a way that's very
powerful, incredibly exciting.
>> Yeah, the poorest people in the world
are being chauffeered around by AIS for
sure. Interesting. Two interesting
points here. The first is it's a
two-seater, right? And of course, the
average load for an Uber is like 1.2
people, right? How many times do we take
an Uber all by ourselves? So, if you
need six people in a car, just take
three of the cyber cabs.
>> Yeah. Not just that, but think about,
you know, a normal cab has four airbags.
You got the airbags for every seat.
Elon in his infinite brilliance is like
we now we only need two air. We cut the
cost of airbags alone in half with this
design. And in the rare instance where
you need three or four people, get two
of them. End of story.
>> Well, they follow each other right
behind each other. It's it's perfectly
great.
>> I I I suspect there's more of a
backstory there, though, with the
two-seater. Remember, Tesla was
originally teasing that it was going to
launch a Model 2, which was going to be
their highly coveted $25,000 car. That
never happened. And my best read of the
the situation is what was originally
planned as the Tesla Model 2 became this
robo taxi because at some point once the
the car the value of the car or the
sales value I should say of the car
crosses below some threshold it makes
more sense to monetize it via autonomous
ride sharing or robo taxi services than
it does to actually sell the car.
>> This will turn transportation into an
API.
>> Yep. You know, interestingly enough,
we're starting to see conversations um
where the other companies that do have
steering wheels and pedals
and uh LARs are saying, "Oh, I'm not
sure that, you know, the cyber cab is
safe enough. It does it only has
cameras. It doesn't have the other
modalities." So, expect to see a battle
in courts about what city allows this
technology in.
Yeah. Um, Boston just to put a
exclamation point on that.
>> Mayor Woo, come on the podcast and we'll
have a conversation about it.
>> Oh, yeah. Do that. That'd be awesome.
>> Uh, I'm going to continue the uh this uh
conversation. Let's shift it now to the
global stage. Uh, the competition is
going three-sided. The Financial Times
reported that Uber is partnering with
traditional taxi fleets to complement uh
and compete against Whimo's expanding
robo taxi service. So, you know, a
strategic alliance between ride hailing
and traditional taxis to counter
autonomous vehicles that don't need
humans. You know, think about what that
means. You know, Uber, the company that
disrupted taxis, is now partnering with
taxis to fight the companies that are
disrupting them. Meanwhile, The Verge
reported that Uber and UK based robo
taxi company Wave officially launched
services in London. Immad, have you seen
Wave yet?
>> Yeah, I've seen it. It's just starting
to roll out. Uh, so I'm looking forward
to getting my first ride on that.
>> Yeah. And and CNBC reported that Whimo
and Zuks announced simultaneous
expansion into new cities, uh,
including, uh, with along with Tesla and
Nevada, California, and Texas. So, you
know, my prediction here is that we're
going to see at least five different
autonomous electric robo taxi companies
fighting it out major cities inside the
next year, driving the cost as low as
possible. Right? So, the cost of
personalized transport is basically
dropping to the cost of electricity.
It's demonetized mobility. It's the
entire abundance thesis. The cost is
dropping to the cost of charging a
battery. And the ultimate winner is the
public, unless you live in Boston. So,
[laughter]
>> do we
>> Well, no. Cambridge might Cambridge
might have a chance. Actually, that'll
put a lot of pressure on Boston. That'd
be awesome if Cambridge
>> beat Boston by
trying to take a taxi and it stops at
the Harvard Bridge.
>> That's right. The bridges are are no
fly, no drive zones for autonomy,
apparently in the near [laughter]
future.
>> Actually, what's funny is you can get
around to Harvard, but you wouldn't be
able to go to Harvard Business School.
>> That's really cool.
>> Yeah. What's going to happen though when
you get your Tesla Optimus robot and it
has the drive program? So it can drive
for you in whatever car you have without
retro.
>> Ah, there you go.
>> It'll get banned in Boston, too. I'm
sure [laughter]
in Boston.
>> You know, I I want to hit the economics
here because uh you know, the the Whimos
are pricing out the new version of the
Whimos are pricing out over $100,000. Uh
the cyber cab is coming in at or below
$30,000. And what's most interesting in
my mind is the winner here is going to
be whoever can mass manufacture these
the fastest. And Elon's going to win
that game. I mean, he's the guy that
builds the machines that builds the
machines.
>> Look, clearly
>> in the US maybe, but China is is dumping
some might say into Europe. So, it's
it's not a US-on game is is the issue.
>> You're going to end up with all of them
for the for the foreseeable future. And
I think Peter, the point you made is the
most important one. The end user wins.
>> Yeah. Uh Dave, do you remember when we
were at uh at the Gigafactory and we're
being toured around and we saw outside
the giant mounds of aluminum scrap
metal? Yeah.
>> And then the smelter
>> and then the Model Y press. And it was
like just this beautiful orchestration.
It's incredible. End to end
>> and and you can actually walk with the
car from the day it's the minute it's
born. It's like a it's a long walk, you
know? It's almost a mile, but a car
comes out the other end. And but you're
literally watching every part get put on
as you walk with it. It's absolutely
wild.
>> Yeah, it's beautiful.
>> But it's amazing to me in the in the
Cyber Cab how few parts there are. Like
when you open the hood of your gas
guzzler car and you look at all the
stuff that's in there and then you look
inside the equivalent cyber cab, it
really feels like there's maybe one
tenth as many things.
>> Um I've got a hard use a lot here which
is a typical car is 2,000 moving parts
in the drivetrain and the Tesla has 17.
>> And I an IC internal combustion engine
car.
>> Yeah.
>> 2,000 moving parts versus unbelievable.
>> Yeah. So, in terms of maintenance,
design, you know, all of that stuff.
This is why the car dealers are all
freaked out. You never need to
>> I was, you know, last time I was in New
York, I was in a yellow cab. I'm like,
why is this thing so disgusting? It
smells like a public urinal. Why? Why
are they all like this? But then you
think about what happens to that cab.
You know, the medallion is incredibly
valuable. It gets handed from one driver
to the next. You know, it never stops
moving. And then at night, in the middle
of the night, uh, somebody drives it
home and then they hand they get up
first thing in the morning, they start
driving it again. But it has to take
somebody home. The cyber cab goes to get
cleaned in the middle of the night when
there's nothing to do. It goes to a
place, could be anywhere. It could be in
Queens, way, gets itself cleaned, and
comes back
>> pristine. And that's it's just night and
day when you get into one of these
versus a a cab. Now, they're brand new,
so maybe that's part of it, too. But the
experience is night and day better.
>> And they look beautiful.
>> So what happens when they break down? I
guess a a cyber truck comes and towes it
away.
>> Yeah.
>> Door dashers come over to help is is the
recent story. I guess
>> the door is wedged open and can't be
closed.
>> Maybe they just squash it into a metal
cube right there. Crush it
>> and recycle it.
>> Take it back to the smelter. [laughter]
>> That's mean.
Oh,
>> we'll pull out the GPUs first.
>> Yeah.
>> All right, I'm going to move us on uh to
the space arena. Two fun stories on the
space frontier today. In our first
story, NASA chose Blue Origin to build
the telecommunications relay network on
Mars. The comm infrastructure that will
connect future Mars missions back to
Earth. Uh this is the infrastructure
layer for the Mars economy. Whoever owns
the telecom network controls the
bandwidth on Earth. There's a companies
like AT&T on Mars. It could be Blue
Origin. Uh, and you might wonder why did
NASA select Blue Origin, not SpaceX
since SpaceX, you know, owns and
operates the world's or space's largest
space-based laser linked comm network.
And um, ultimately this is the
government, you know, keeping two
competitors, two suppliers in business,
giving them each a slice of the pie. And
regardless of Blue Origin having won the
NASA contract, I guarantee you Elon will
still build Starlink around Mars, uh,
ultimately what we're seeing here is the
birth of the interplanetary internet.
Alex, you excited about this one?
>> Look, Mars had it coming. The moon had
it coming. We're going to build the
Dyson swarm. Someone was going to get
awarded the the Starlink for Mars. Uh,
it's interesting that it went to Jeff
Bezos's company and not to Elon's, but I
I'm fully expecting that we're going to
have a very very competitive
interplanetary internet and I'm frankly
I'm I'm glad that there are vendors that
are competing for for Mars coms other
than SpaceX.
>> Yeah. But it's going to be a packet
switch network throughout the inner
solar system. Mars asteroids
>> high latency, but that's all right.
>> Yeah. Until we get faster and light uh
comms, who knows? Physics.
>> Time will tell.
>> Time will tell. Are you working on that,
Alex?
>> Can't say.
>> Well, the the the physics that we have
right now suggests that faster than
light travel is not possible.
>> Don't bum me out here. Okay. [laughter]
Sorry to break the bad news. The
physics, the textbook physics right now
says that super luminal travel,
>> then we have the wrong physics.
>> Uh [laughter]
>> we'll find out. Just hope.
>> Yeah.
>> Let's move us to another fun story in
space. Our second story, and it's a big
one. NASA's Nancy Grace Roman Space
Telescope has launched on a Falcon Heavy
carrying a field of view of more than
100 times greater than Hubble and the
ability to scan the sky for more than a
thousand times faster. The Roman
telescope is designed to discover tens
of thousands of new worlds and map the
distribution of dark matter across the
universe. Uh before we discuss it, let's
play a video by our amazing NASA
administrator Jared Isaacman, friend of
the pod. And I love this guy. He's such
a good communicator. Let's check it out.
>> Oh, the telescope is very healthy right
now. It's making its 1 million mile
journey to Lrange Point2. It's going to
look for what we think will be up to a
100,000 additional exoplanets and other
star systems. It's going to help us
understand dark energy, dark matter. And
as you saw during the press conference,
President Trump called in. This is a
really exciting time in America's space
program right now.
>> What's the difference between this
telescope and the Hubble?
>> It's hundreds of times more powerful. I
mean, the field of view is is over a
hundred times greater than Hubble. Its
scan rate is over a thousand times
greater. Uh I mean, this is a this is
going to be a household name like Hubble
and James. This is America's next great
exploration asset.
>> And you say it's going to help you find
planets hiding behind planets,
>> planets hiding behind other stars,
distant stars. The light can blind it
out. This will it has a special JPL
coronagraph that helps us find these
hidden worlds. I mean tens of thousands
of additional worlds we're gonna find.
>> Tens of thousands of worlds. Amazing.
>> Yeah. Jared Jared is incredible, isn't
he? Compare that to that interview of
Sam saying, "Why is this new model
different? Why is Astra different for
people?" Compare his answer to what
Jared just did to answer this this
question. It's like night and day. I
mean, he is a great great communicator.
>> Yeah. And interestingly data
>> interestingly this is going to finally
start to give us statistics over the
number of habitable at least earth
recognizable habitable worlds it's being
pointed toward the center of our galaxy
and we'll just be able to do large
sweeps of the sky looking in part it has
other missions as well but looking in
part for microl lensing events for
planets that are crossing in front
exoplanets crossing in front of their
respective stars causing the uh via
their gravity causing light from those
stars to be very weakly increased
briefly due to these microl lensing
events. The downside,
>> you know what's so
>> yeah what's so cool about that is on the
last podcast Peter asked us uh you know
sim you missed it and amad you weren't
here. Uh but you know what's your answer
to the fermy paradox like why why are we
not seeing other civilizations? But one
of the theories is that there are many
many civilizations talking to each other
near the center of the galaxy where you
can get from star to star in, you know,
a year or two as opposed to where we
are. We're way out in the wings where
it's like so far away.
>> We're in the unfashionable outer suburbs
of the galaxy. That's right. [laughter]
>> So, you know, who knows? This could
>> I I I'm actually happy we're here. You
know, the galactic center is a really
dangerous place to be. [laughter]
You don't like supernova, Peter?
>> I don't like the radiation flux they
deliver. No.
>> I'm reminded of the opening scene of
Hitchhocker's Guide to the Galaxy where
they're bulldozing Earth to make a
hyperspace g highway
>> bypass. Yeah. Yeah.
>> I mean, I I love this. Uh, you know, I'm
curious to our viewers, and if you can,
you know, let us know in the notes. uh
would you like us to have a conversation
uh on the current UAP disclosure con um
you know uh discussions out there if we
can bring some of the leaders in UAPs
and the whole disclosure scenario. The
White House just released their
disclosure plan. Uh Alex, I don't know
if I'm going to mention that, but I'm
curious if folks want us to have a
conversation on that topic on the pod.
Alex, would you mention uh the recent
White House announcement? Yeah, there
was some reporting out there from Avi's
UAP science advisory council. One of the
members of the council mentioned that in
a recent briefing that this council,
which as I understand it was stood up by
the White House, was informed that the
White House had prepared uh disclosure
plan for informing the general public of
the existence of non-human intelligence,
which if accurate reporting, it that's
pretty interesting.
>> Yeah. Iman, how do where do you come out
on the whole UAP side of the equation?
I'm curious.
>> I actually have no position on it. I've
never thought about it properly.
[clears throat]
>> Okay.
>> I'd like to see um strong claims require
strong evidence.
>> I stand in that.
>> A lot of people would say there is
strong evidence. It's just hidden.
But we shall see. No, I'm with See. I I
would say evidence I really it would be
highly desirable for there to be a
prepoundonderance of evidence that
everyone can go and see and touch and
experiment on. I I think that's probably
the gold standard of uh in in an ideal
outcome if there were uh a White House
disclosure event. If if the president
goes into what's left of the rose garden
and gives a speech and says we're not
alone, then ideally part two, paragraph
two of the speech would be to hold up or
otherwise present some artifacts that uh
that would be subject to extreme
scientific scrutiny to support the
claim.
>> That would be a fun conversation to
have. All right, our third our final
subject for today. Uh three major health
and longevity stories came out this
week. Uh the first is that OpenAI
expanded GPT health features to connect
directly to patient records and
healthcare databases. They integrated uh
the integration brings Epic electronic
health records data into chat GPT for
healthcare and Epic as you guys probably
know is the largest collection of health
records. 325 million patients are inside
Epic roughly the entire US population.
Clinicians can now pull appointment
notes, lab results, medications, and ask
questions across patients entire record.
And consumers uh can now connect their
Apple Health, One Medical, Function
Health. So, ChatPT can help you
understand your test results, prepare
for your doctor appointments, and get
personalized data and diet workout
advice. So, that's the first story. Uh
the second story, uh interestingly
enough, we talked about it last week. We
mentioned that the FDA had approved a
drug called uh Duraxinarissib. It rolls
off the tongue onto the floor uh for the
first targeted RA inhibitor for
metastatic pancreatic adnocarcinoma
attacking the RAS family of proteins
that drive tumor growth in most patients
with disease. This week, NBC News
reported that the same drug is showing
promise to treat lung cancer. As
mentioned last week, the RAS mutation
family drives roughly 30% of all human
cancers and was long considered
undruggable, the subject of decades of
failed attempts, but now during the
singularity, the end of cancer is now
within reach. Uh, Alex. Yeah, I think
we're starting to see and and
interestingly I I'm not sure that AI was
actually essential for this particular
drug, but I I think I I think there
there's so much progress being made in
cancer therapies now, including on the
imunotherapy side that we're starting I
think to see the emergence of and again
caveat caveat caveat universal cancer
treatments, universal cancer vaccines in
some cases where after years and years
of treating cancer answer as thousands
of different diseases. We're starting to
finally get to the point where we can
start to treat to move upchain uh
upstream and start to treat if not root
causes at at least identify treatments
that whether it's proteomic pathways on
the one hand or immunologic pathways on
the other start to have treatments andor
vaccines that can treat multiple classes
of cancer. And I think that's
>> cancer's cooked. Yeah. that cancer
should have been cooked long ago. Was it
Nixon who announced the the war on
cancer? Uh it it took a forever to get
to this point, more than half a century.
And it's an interesting counterfactual
experiment, I thought experiment. Is
there anything knowing what we know now
that we could have done 50 or 100 years
ago to radically accelerate the onset of
broadspectctrum cancer treatments? What
do you think, Peter?
I think the data I mean we've known for
example about the RAS mutation uh you
know basically causing unconstrained
growth for some time. It's just you know
getting getting the molecules and
getting the drugs that can attack it
properly. Uh I think the tools we have
right now are just finally giving us
that that reach. Uh and then being able,
you know, we talked about cell
simulators, being able to understand
fundamentally what happens and how to
block it is what's coming. Immod this is
an area of personal passion for you as
well. You've been deep into medical AI.
>> Yeah. So I said the this wasn't AI kind
of on the thing, but the range of
treatments now coming out on the cancer
side gives a lot of hope to what's going
to come. I think the mRNA one maybe is
more general um that we saw recently.
And I think you know the first part of
that integrating into the epic health
records actually applying AI across the
board like we should have a sprint so
that within a year or two max every
single health decision is double checked
by an AI. We should have
>> more more than that I think it's going
to become malpractice
>> to diagnose a patient without AI in the
loop
>> right we already know AI is a far better
physician a diagnostician than a human
is
>> so I think you should have a series of
approved edge and cloud models and every
time you make a diagnosis the AI has to
have had one check that will save so
many lives it will detect so many
cancers and then it's about how do we
increase the level and volume of
information because Even now the type of
data we have around cancer and other
conditions that we absorb is tiny
compared to the amount that we could
have with the AI transforming it. So I
think that yeah let's cook disease let's
get rid of it. No one should have to die
of cancer and it's something we should
be really directed at. And
>> on the first story
>> go on sorry please. It's just like it's
very strange that you know as we have
the genesis programs and others there
isn't just a straightforward we now have
the capability to potentially cure this
stuff. Let's direct $10 billion towards
it. It's tractable.
>> I think the the story on Epic is
interesting right having been involved
in that business through Fountain Life.
you know, Epic is the majority
uh you know, electronic health record in
the US and it's been a bear to navigate
for for physicians and and patients have
never had access. So, putting an AI
layer on top of that is awesome.
Yeah. Um let me move it to our last
story here in uh in the area of health.
uh it's related to what may be called
the first longevity class of drugs the
GLP1s. So a new a new paper published
just two days ago on September 2nd in
nature shows that semiglutide the active
ingredient in ompic and wagi
recapitulates many of the benefits of
caloric restriction and get this it's in
female mice just to be clear and extends
the lifespan of mice by almost 100 days
in humans that's the equivalent of 8 to
10 years. Uh the study found that GLP-1R
activation initiated late in life in
these mice uh accentuates age associated
decline and uh modulates conservative
genetic regions for aging functioning as
a caloric caloric restriction mimedic.
Also this week it was reported that
Gilip 1 drugs also are being linked to
fewer serious infections including
tuberculosis and you guys already know
that tuberculosis is the deadliest
killer on earth. You know killing over
1.25 25 million people per year. So the
same drug that's treating diabetes,
obesity, dise, you know, kidney disease,
cardiovascular disease, and addiction
may also be extending lifespan and
reducing infectious disease. One
molecule, six diseases and still
counting. Um I, you know, again, Alex,
you made the point that this might be
the beginning of longevity escape
velocity. I think th this is like to the
extent that with the benefit of uh
hindsight we look back in a few years
and we say you idiots of course you were
on the verge you you were seeing the
sparks of longevity escape velocity you
had the the GLP1s it to the extent that
that's the case I don't think it should
be that surprising what's more
mystifying to me is from an evolutionary
perspective if the GLP1 RA class of
molecules is capable of doing everything
from treating infections to extending
life expectancy to modulating diabetes,
>> reducing addiction and compulsive uh
behaviors. If it does like all of this,
why on earth wasn't like why did not why
did we not evolve with uh with either
this ability to to modulate our own
semiglutide class molecules in our
system or maybe a slightly more cynical
angle. I if if it turns out that the
reason why GLP1s are so effective at so
many diseases is that these diseases
somehow are diseases of quote unquote
modern lifestyles and that we just like
it's treating all of the diseases of
modernity and that's why we never
evolved the solution. Addiction to
compulsive gambling or alcohol addiction
uh or overeating of sugar that these are
all relatively modern diseases. That's
why this it's basically a treatment for
for modernity. That would be pretty
ironic.
>> So, I just want to make a point to the
listening audience. First of all, talk
to your physician about this. This is
not medical advice. Yes.
>> But I use I use uh a Jill P1 drug. I
don't know if any of you do right now.
And I use it not for weight loss, right?
I've been on my fighting weight for a
while. My percent body fat is
substantially, you know, because I work
out and I'm very careful about what I
eat. I use it as a longevity drug
because of all the benefits we just
heard about.
>> Um, got two
>> I know you're using one.
>> Yeah, I'm using one and I just got my
blood test done and my liver enzymes are
50% better. Uh, which is pretty amazing.
Uh, which means I can drink more. No,
just kidding. [laughter]
That's not the point.
>> I know that's not the point.
>> You're supposed to not want to drink it.
>> I know. Um the so there's there's
there's that but I think you know to
Alex to your point earlier right
remember that evolution has birthed us
for death right we we've had short life
cycles so that you are the cycle time of
evolution can work more quickly we're
breaking through that now uh and living
through that so I think it may have been
engineered or evolutionary engineered
that we died at different levels and
this is a long history where we used to
die of heart disease or we used to die
of bacterial illnesses and then we
figured that out then we died of heart
disease. We got some sense of that now
we're dying of cancer and then as we
break
>> then explain then See explain
tuberculosis if if you're in a
tuberculosis rich environment surely
evolution would favor any molecule that
could just be amplified up that would
help prevent uh young and reproductive
entities from surviving tuberculosis
infection. Well, you I go back to the
you know there's lots of pathogens going
after us all the time, right? Billions
of them because they're all trying to
survive in their own way, including
cancer. Uh the uh capability of the
human body to navigate this has never
been needed until we started pushing the
boundaries to this level. Now we do
>> and and Selene my thesis you know and
I've spoken about this pretty widely is
the reason for the life cycle is not
more rapid evolution. It's that for most
of human existence you know
[clears throat] homo sapiens came on the
scene roughly 200,000 years ago food was
very scarce and if our primary mission
is to perpetuate our species the last
thing you want to do is steal food from
your grandchildren's mouths. So the best
thing you could do is die. Reproduce and
die basically, right? And so we see, you
know, the human body, and people should
know this, you're in uh you're in sort
of prime condition until your late 20s.
Uh back 200,000 years ago, you'd go into
puberty at age 13, 12 or 13. You'd be
pregnant immediately, no birth control.
By the time you were 26, 27, 28, you're
a grandparent, and then you would die so
you didn't steal food from your
grandchildren's mouths. And
>> and so We never had any
>> that's my joke about marriage that we
invented marriage to keep the parents
together the till the kids were
self-sufficient average lifespan was 25
years old from the most of human history
we invented marriage about 6,000 years
ago and it's definitely true then
marriage is not designed for uh 50 60
year lifespans it's designed literally
for
>> no no watching this one of my relatives
calls it state sanctioned torture um
marriage [laughter] because the we have
the job of now evolving the institution
to deal with the conditions today
compared to when we first invented it.
And I use that example because it
applies to all our institutions,
democracies, educational systems, legal
systems, healthare systems. This I think
is the biggest work we have to do is as
we blow past all these limitations, we
have to reinvent all of the institutions
which are the scaffolding that keep
humanity safe and civilized.
>> Hopefully, we have a benevolent AI to
help us do all that.
>> We'll need it. And if not, Benevolent
AI. At least we'll have GLP ones.
[laughter]
[snorts]
>> All right, time for some conversations
with the mates. Uh, we've got some
questions here. Uh, Emmod, I'm going to
give you first crack.
>> All right. Uh, if money becomes
obsolete, how will desirable land be
allocated? Is everyone just locked into
their beach house forever? By nick
52547.
This is an interesting one. I think that
you know Elon and others have said that
money might become obsolete. I've said
that you can't compete with robots. I
think this is a question of kind of land
rights and more. Um because typically
where you see reallocation is in
upheavalss. So the way that we're going
without the right structures, you'll
probably have a debt jubilee. You'll
probably have chaos and land
redistribution.
But if we can actually navigate through
it, then land rights and property rights
should be enforced and so you can keep
your beach house. But the number of
desirable locations will go up
dramatically because you will have air
taxis, self-driving cars, solar panels,
and self-driving
construction workers. So
>> yeah, exactly. Self-driving construction
workers.
>> Yes.
>> Nice. See,
>> uh let me take number four. Uh do you
think AI will evolve past this risk
averse bottleneck that we're currently
in? And that's from ads susie1073.
Um uh yes that's the hopefully but
hopefully we move towards calibrated
risk rather than recklessness because
right now we we treat uncertainty as
kind of like a reason to refuse right
and that's a technical problem but
there's all the legal and policy issues
around this. Uh when you're raising kids
one of the things they teach you teach
kids is are you taking a responsible
risk? Um and we need to apply that same
kind of paradigm to this model. Could
you create something like a risk budget
which is what can an AI decide? How much
can it uh spend on that? What systems
can it access? What triggers escalation?
Right? And we need to get very
sophisticated around this. Um models
need to become better at distinguishing
uh uh dangerous intent from uh real
expert usage, right? because you can't
get to you can't just say remove the
guard rails. It's got to be dynamic uh
where you deal with proportionality on
user identity, the context, uh the
reversibility of that. So we'll get AI
maturity when we can say here's the
risk, here's the confidence I have in
this and here's the reversible next
step. Uh, and then rather than just
saying no, I think that we need to get a
lot more nuance around this. And
unfortunately, in today's world, nuance
has no part to play in the soundbite
politics that we have out there.
>> All right, Dave, over to you.
>> All right, I'll take number one. Uh, can
you see a way to turn libraries into
centers of AI development and physical
AI training for everyone from Train with
John Koalo?
Um,
yeah. Yes, but there's a bigger issue
which is there's a huge amount of white
collar office space and white collar
work is turning to AI. At the same time,
we have declining population espec
especially working age population. So
there's a bigger issue of what about all
this other space? What are we going to
do with it all? It's very similar to
what happened with the shopping malls
after online shopping became huge and
then COVID hit and a lot of people were
thinking there's got to be something
really great we can use with all this
shopping mall space. But there were some
ideas but for the most part didn't work
out that it all got replaced. So I think
um there are lots of ideas for what you
can do with the library space. You don't
really need the library books anymore
obviously. Uh this is another reason why
you should want data centers in your
community. It's one of the few things
that will reliably grow tax revenue
create job opportunities in a community.
So there are ideas, but I'm not super
optimistic that all the space will be
well utilized going forward.
>> And there are programs in inner cities
right now that are, you know, running AI
tutoring in libraries. Uh that does that
does exist.
>> Uh Alex
diamond chips.
>> I get the fun one. So question number
two, whatever happened to synthetic
diamond chips for computers? And this is
from Asterene. So here's the problem
with diamond. Pure diamond is an
insulator. It has a band gap of
approximately 5 1/2 electron volts. So
it really doesn't want to be a good
computer. To make it into a good
computer, at least a good computer of a
recognizable cosy type, you have to dope
it. That's hard. If I had to steal the
case for diamondbased
recognizable computers, it would be for
ultraigh temperature environments where
such a wide band gap could be
advantageous or maybe very high voltage
environments where again a large band
gap could be advantageous. It's not an
enormous market. Could be wrong, maybe
I'll be wrong. Doesn't seem like an
enormous market. Where I'm much more
bullish on diamonds is for sensing. So
you you can put what are called nitrogen
vacancies uh or NV centers into
diamonds. Basically put an extra
unwanted nitrogen atom into a diamond
lattice and suddenly you get an
exquisitly sensitive magnetic field or
just field in general sensor because of
an an extra vacancy that is introduced
as a result of the diamond. So, diamonds
for quantum sensing, super interesting.
Potentially, it's not investment advice,
but I I think technologically it's very
attractive. One could imagine at some
point in the future, diamond chips for
sensing even get us to sci-fi tech like
wearable MRI sensors. Diamond chips for
computing? Eh, probably not.
>> Why did I know you'd have an answer for
that one?
>> It's [laughter] interesting.
>> All right, See, first choice is yours,
pal. Um
um
uh I will go with number seven. Uh when
do we get a forecast for when data
center energy sources transition from
gas turbine farms to nuclear and SMRs?
Uh short fairly easy answer here. You
know gas dominates the current buildout.
Uh SMRs going to be in the next 3 to
four years. The reason people are
getting so excited is that nuclear is an
engineering problem, not an invention
problem, right? Fusion is still in the
invention problem category. Um, and the
so you've got this impedance mismatch of
data centers taking two or three years
to build. Nuclear is taking a bit
longer. Um, we will get there I think
faster than people think with SMRs, but
I think it would still be a while. So,
so take it uh two three years for the
initial wave of of SMRs and then five to
seven years for the big buildout. So, I
think what's going to end up happening
is AI is going to do for nuclear what
what smartphones did for batteries like
it just created such huge demand that
the massive innovation there was a huge
acceleration in the innovation curve.
>> Nice. And we had a fantastic pod with
Rome Nom on energy. If you guys haven't
seen it, please check it out. You know,
his Yeah, he talks about pretty much
that time frame. Uh
>> that's where I get all my good
information about energy.
>> Yeah. Alex, let's go to you.
>> All right. Well, I I think I have to
answer question number eight seems to be
directed toward me. So, eight asks, "How
far away from Alpha Centtory do you
actually have to aim to reach it when it
arrives?" And this is from typical dad
pi. So to to three significant figures.
So I to the extent I understand this
question uh let me give you the
semiofficial firmy explorer line. So on
the last pod we had Matt Pines and
Philip Johnston announcing for for those
who who didn't watch humanity's first
mission to Alpha Centuri and
>> and and I'm involved. I've I'm involved.
What can I say? Uh I'm I'm in a lot of
rooms. Uh so the under the official
mission parameters for the the Fermy
explorer mission the goal is to get at
least 99% of the way to Alpha Centuri.
So uh Alpha Centtory approximately four
light years away. So you could do the
math and and that turns out to be
4100ths uh of uh of a lightyear call it
uh precision getting there. And that's
from Earth. So if if I put my sci-fi hat
on and extrapolate a bit, I think that
in the next few years on board and and
maybe I should add parenthetically,
Firmeny Explore mission is intended to
launch by 2029.
I suspect this this is not an official
position for Fermy Explorer mission. I
suspect that when the mission comes to
full fruition and is launched, I suspect
it will have active guidance on board.
Uh and if that's the case, this 99% of
the way to Alpha Centtory, not an
official position, will turn into or can
turn into 100%. Uh in in the sense that
it actually hits the Alpha Centuri
system, not just 4/10en of uh or 4100s
rather of a lightyear away. That said,
Fermy Explorer is intended to reach
Alpha Centtory 80,000 years from now,
which is perhaps inconvenient from the
perspective of mission verification. if
you actually want to [clears throat] get
it. But I I actually
>> GLP1 drugs.
>> We're going to need a lot of GLP1s for
this. I I think I think we'll get to the
whole point of of the mission is that
we're supposed to beat the Fermy
Explorer and get there sooner. This is
just the first one to launch.
>> Amazing. Dave, over to you, pal.
>> All right, I'll take number six. Are
data centers using closed loop
geothermal cooling also noisy or are
they quieter? And that is from Asterene.
uh they should be dead quiet just like
geothermal heating is dead quiet. Also
uh nuclear reactors that are ocean you
know near the ocean use geothermal
cooling and ocean cooling and they're
dead quiet. So it should be very very
quiet. But also you know regular data
centers that are using liquid cooling
are only noisy because the water gets
cooled outside with these really poorly
designed fans. There's no reason for
that. If your if your regulatory body
says, "Yeah, you can build a data center
here, but it has to be quiet."
Guaranteed they will build the data
center quiet, there's no reason those
external fans need to make any noise.
>> Instead of making them illegal, cities
need to be saying, "These are our
requirements. Drop our energy costs, you
know, make them quiet, invest in our
infrastructure." And they will, and they
will.
>> Uh, Immod looks like number five is for
you.
>> That's an interesting one. They talk
about a sun shade there. What scale of
satellites in terms of
>> we talked about
>> that came up on the last pod. You missed
it. Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. And what scale of satellite terms
square meters required to actually
impact global temperatures?
>> Uh I would say if you whack something in
the sun earth lrange point a couple of
million km out you need about a couple
of million km squared. So about the size
of India would knock a a degrees Celsius
off. That's bigger than anything we've
ever managed. But, you know, it's worth
a try. Why not?
>> Yeah. And
>> maybe convert the moon.
>> Mercury, please.
>> Mercury.
>> Or [snorts] or a series. Yeah. And I I
still love the the sun shade, you know,
putting a thermometer be able to titrate
the solar flux on the planet.
>> I think it's a trick, for what it's
worth, I think that's a trick question.
I I think with a sufficiently good AI
planetary scale model, we could make uh
any sun shade or or other satellite
intervention dimminimous size. It's just
a matter of appropriately perturbing the
the Earth atmospheric system with enough
AI.
>> Okay.
>> All right. Uh as before, we love your
outro videos. Please send it to us. We
want to see your creative nature. You
send it to media dmandis.com. The team
will uh show it to us and then we'll air
it. And again, last shot. If you want to
join us on our AMA, we have two AMAs
coming up on Zoom with all the mates to
answer your questions. We're going to do
one in the morning to help hit Europe
and Asia, one in the afternoon, early
evening to get everybody in the United
States. You'll have a chance to ask us
all your questions. Go to moonshots.com
and register. It'll be up there just for
a couple of days and then we're done.
All right. Uh Immad, I think this is the
first music video that includes you. Uh
which I appreciate. Let's
>> There have been others. I remember
others.
>> Okay. Well, the first one I remember.
>> All right, this one is Supersonic
Tsunami. Uh, and thank you so much to uh
Chromatoss for your for your submission.
[music]
Can you smell that in the kitchen? Some
uncooked academic invention overshadowed
[music and singing]
by gatekeeper hysteria.
Answers to major problem areas. And
that's all it takes.
A moonshot [singing and music] and
willing mistakes. If breaking the moon
makes you mad,
[laughter] remember it's just a launch
pad. Abundance we will foster
while we [singing and music] live long
and prosper. Riding the wave of autonomy
[music] formed from supersonic tsunami.
[singing]
[music]
The takes are considered [singing]
sometimes hot but investment advice.
This is not the analysis. Brilliant
never tring [music]
[singing] pointed balls and strikes.
Someday [music] we'll disassemble the
moon. Deal with [singing] every elephant
in the room. Destroy all financial
disparities. [music]
Don't sleep through the singularity.
Abundance we will foster [singing]
while we live long and [music] prosper
riding the wave [singing] of autonomy
formed from supersonic tsunami.
>> All right to the beach.
>> That was awesome. Enjoy the umbrella
drink.
>> Thank you.
>> All right for an amazing pod.
>> Hey, make sure you're uploading.
>> It'll never get slower. See you next
week.
>> [music]